<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Epistolium-vagum-prosa-metricum: or, An epistle at randome, in prose and metre. To be delivered, to all whom it may concern; but, was first intended only, for two or three of the authors friends in authority (if he hath so many left) to mediate in Parliament, the redress of his destructive grievances; in the expression whereof, many particulars of publick concernment are interwoven. The author, is George Wither Esq; who, in writing this address, being transported beyond the sense of his personal sufferings, discovers by a poetical rapture, that whereon the peace of these nations depends; and, what is, and what vvill be, their sad condition; as also, what new-purgatories, and fiery-tryals, they are likely to pass, if God's mercy, prevents not: which that they may endeavour to obtain, their old remembrancer gives them, once more, a fore-warning; resolving, this shall be his last time, of sounding them an alarm.</title>
            <author>Wither, George, 1588-1667.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 171 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96748</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3156</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E763_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204085</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863787</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863787</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116002</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96748)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116002)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 117:E763[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Epistolium-vagum-prosa-metricum: or, An epistle at randome, in prose and metre. To be delivered, to all whom it may concern; but, was first intended only, for two or three of the authors friends in authority (if he hath so many left) to mediate in Parliament, the redress of his destructive grievances; in the expression whereof, many particulars of publick concernment are interwoven. The author, is George Wither Esq; who, in writing this address, being transported beyond the sense of his personal sufferings, discovers by a poetical rapture, that whereon the peace of these nations depends; and, what is, and what vvill be, their sad condition; as also, what new-purgatories, and fiery-tryals, they are likely to pass, if God's mercy, prevents not: which that they may endeavour to obtain, their old remembrancer gives them, once more, a fore-warning; resolving, this shall be his last time, of sounding them an alarm.</title>
                  <author>Wither, George, 1588-1667.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the year 1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Partly in verse.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "sept: 19.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament. --  House of Commons --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116002:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>EPISTOLIUM-VAGUM-PROSA-METRICUM: OR, An Epiſtle at Randome, IN <hi>PROSE</hi> and <hi>METRE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To be delivered, to all whom it may concern; but, was firſt intended only, for two or three of the <hi>Authors</hi> Friends in Authority (if he hath ſo many left) to medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate in <hi>Parliament,</hi> the Redreſs of his <hi>deſtructive Grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces;</hi> in the expreſsion whereof, many Particulars of Publick Concernment are interwoven.</p>
            <q>
               <l>When <hi>Juſtice</hi> raigns, the <hi>Land</hi> doth flouriſh;</l>
               <l>When, 'tis unthron'd, the <hi>People periſh.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>The Author, is <hi>George Wither</hi> Eſq; Who, in writing this <hi>Addreſs,</hi> being tranſported beyond the ſenſe of his <hi>Perſonal Sufferings,</hi> diſcovers by a <hi>Poetical Rapture,</hi> that whereon the peace of theſe <hi>Nations</hi> depends; and, what IS, and what VVILL BE, their <hi>ſad Condition;</hi> as alſo, what <hi>New-Purgatories,</hi> and <hi>Fiery-Tryals,</hi> they are likely to paſs, if GOD's Mercy, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents not: which that they may endeavour to obtain, their old REMEMBRANCER gives them, once more, a <hi>Fore-warning;</hi> reſolving, this ſhall be his <hi>Laſt Time,</hi> of ſounding them an <hi>ALARM.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>When <hi>Diſreſpects,</hi> to <hi>Wrongs,</hi> doth Ruine adde,</l>
               <l>He, may be <hi>wiſe,</hi> who ſeems a little <hi>mad;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And, in that FIT ſpeak things that needfull be</l>
               <l>To turn thoſe men, that are, <hi>more mad then he.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London,</hi> in the Year 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116002:2"/>
            <head>Auguſt 10. 1659. <hi>Epistolium-Vagum-Proſa-metricum:</hi> OR, An EPISTLE at Randome, in Proſe and Metre.</head>
            <div type="prose">
               <p>OUr <hi>Engliſh Proverb</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Charity begins at home;</hi> and, this Divine Precept, <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf,</hi> implies, that there ought to be in every man ſuch a moderate and well-regulated <hi>ſelf-love,</hi> as may be a ſtanding <hi>Rule</hi> whereby to regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late his love to other men: Alſo, from this ſaying of <hi>Paul, He that provides not for his family, is worſe then an infidel;</hi> I do collect, that, <hi>He who provides not for himſelf, is worſe then a Beaſt:</hi> It is every mans duty, in order to the preſervation of his <hi>Country,</hi> to preſerve him alſo, as much as he can, who loves and ſtudies the peace and welfare of it; and I knowing no man living, who affects the welfare thereof, more then I do, may be culpable perhaps of unfaithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to my <hi>Country,</hi> by neglecting my own preſervation. Therefore, that, I may diſcharge the duty which I owe to my <hi>Country,</hi> my <hi>Self,</hi> and my <hi>Neighbours,</hi> by taking timely care of my own preſervation, (being at preſent in much hazard, and by none elſe regarded) I have ſent abroad this <hi>wandring Epiſtle</hi> to fetch in aid; which if it come into ſuch hands as I purpoſed it ſhould, and to whom I did firſt, and principally intend it; then, you, who are now peruſing it, are none of thoſe <hi>Idol-Gods,</hi> who are inſenſible of thoſe <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Complaints,</hi> which are preſented unto them; Or, one of <hi>thoſe men in honour without underſtanding, who are like the Beaſts that periſh:</hi> but, one in whom I hope to finde that Candor and Humanity, which renders men heedful and ſenſible of their Neighbours <hi>Grievances:</hi> In that hope, and on that account onely, I am emboldned here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to crave your furthering the preſentation of that my <hi>Petition</hi> &amp; <hi>Narrative</hi> to this <hi>Parliament,</hi> which (if no other charitable hand ſhall firſt undertake it) you ſhall receive in <hi>Writing,</hi> to be preſented to the <hi>Houſe;</hi> and alſo printed Copies of them for your private Information touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my <hi>Cauſe,</hi> with two <hi>Preparatory Addreſſes,</hi> directed to every <hi>Individual Member</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Parliament;</hi> if you give me an encouragement thereto, after the receipt hereof, as I hope you will: for, if there hath been offered to this Parliament any <hi>Grievances,</hi> more conſiderable then mine, (all <hi>Circumstances</hi> and <hi>Conſequences</hi> conſidered) I will be contented they ſhould caſt my Cauſe out of their <hi>Houſe,</hi> and me out of this <hi>Commonwealth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am inforced to ſuch a <hi>Whimſie</hi> as this, becauſe, all my endeavours hitherto have been as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effectual, as if I had ſollicited the <hi>Statues</hi> in <hi>Weſtminſter-Abby,</hi> or in <hi>White-hall Garden;</hi> and becauſe, alſo, I, (having lately made tryal) finde no <hi>Member of Parliament,</hi> willing to offer unto it a <hi>Petition</hi> at this buſie time, though a little longer delay may prove deſtructive to me, injurious to many, and diſhonourable to this <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> wherein <hi>Juſtice</hi> hath been already deferred (as to a main part of my <hi>Grievances</hi>) nigh 17 years: For, it will be no little diſhonour, nor a ſlight diſadvantage thereto, if at ſuch a time as this, a faithful ſervant to this <hi>Republick,</hi> after ſo long and great ſufferings as mine, ſhall not ſeaſonably be indemnified from dangers and dama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges (ſoly occaſioned by her <hi>defective Securities</hi> and unperformed <hi>Ingagements</hi>) which will elſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy him: eſpecially, when large <hi>Indulgencies</hi> are granted to her <hi>malicious Enemies</hi> and notorious <hi>Offenders.</hi> Vouchſafe this <hi>Wanderer</hi> ſuch reſpect as it ſhall deſerve; for, it begs not contrary to Law; hath a Paſs, under my hand, who employed it, onely to prevent thoſe <hi>Provocations</hi> which may be occaſioned by being ſlighted in a <hi>Perſonal Addreſs;</hi> and I will take order that it ſhall be no further troubleſome then you pleaſe, after it hath declared my Requeſts.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:116002:3"/>
               <p>I am in a <hi>ſtreight,</hi> from which none under GOD can deliver me, but the <hi>ſupreme Power</hi> of theſe <hi>Nations;</hi> whereto, though it be difficult to procure acceſs, (by reaſon of thoſe <hi>Inſurrections</hi> which are now begun) I am neceſſitated to attempt it; and do conceive that the <hi>ſupreme Authority</hi> now in being is obliged to vouchſafe me <hi>Protection,</hi> yea, and <hi>Hearing</hi> and <hi>Relief</hi> in ſome meaſure, even at this ſeaſon, which may ſeem unſeaſonable. I act in matters concerning <hi>GOD</hi> and my <hi>Soul,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that meaſure of Illumination which he vouchſafeth by his <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Spirit,</hi> neither un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitably judging, or inwardly diſaffecting them who do the like: It is alſo my <hi>Principle</hi> to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit unto that <hi>civil Authority,</hi> which hath the moſt <hi>viſible Power,</hi> and to be <hi>Active</hi> and <hi>Paſſive</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, both for preſervation of the <hi>Common-peace,</hi> and of my <hi>private intereſts,</hi> without much buſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my ſelf in examining how rightfully, or by what means it got into the <hi>Throne;</hi> conſidering how difficult it is for a <hi>private Perſon</hi> to diſcover the <hi>Myſteries of State,</hi> with the many Intricacies wherewithal they are involved; and how dangerous it is, to dive into thoſe <hi>Whirl-pooles,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, are ſo many contrary <hi>Fluctuations.</hi> I content my ſelf, with ſuch a Notion thereof onely, as <hi>GOD</hi> brings to my knowledge; who, hath by his <hi>Word</hi> informed us, that <hi>all Powers that be</hi> (whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they be) <hi>are of him:</hi> And, as I am injoyned obedience by his <hi>Precepts,</hi> to that which is in <hi>preſent</hi> being; ſo, I have the <hi>practiſe</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and of their <hi>Master CHRIST</hi> himſelf to war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant it, who ſubmitted to the <hi>Roman Monarchs</hi> in thoſe times wherein they lived, in all <hi>Civil Matters,</hi> though they were <hi>Infidels,</hi> cruel <hi>Tyrants,</hi> and very wickedly obtained their <hi>Soveraignty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am carried into this <hi>Digreſſion,</hi> to prevent what I know, is ſpoken privately to my diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage; and therefore bear with my proceeding in it a little further. According to this <hi>Principle,</hi> I acted and ſuffered with a <hi>good Conſcience,</hi> whilſt the <hi>ſupreme Power</hi> was divided betwixt the late <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament:</hi> ſo, I did, when it was ſoly in this <hi>Parliament,</hi> and when <hi>GOD</hi> permitted <hi>Oliver Cromwel</hi> to uſurp it, by a <hi>Stratagem,</hi> for a <hi>Correction</hi> due to our ſins (and for our extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary <hi>Experiments,</hi> both by his <hi>Probation,</hi> our <hi>Own,</hi> and <hi>other mens,</hi> in things of higheſt concernment) I endeavoured, during that <hi>Permiſſion,</hi> in my <hi>Place,</hi> and according to my <hi>qualifications,</hi> and by a <hi>Compliance,</hi> ſo far forth as was warrantable, to preſerve the <hi>Common-peace;</hi> to continue a <hi>claim</hi> on the <hi>Peoples</hi> behalf, of their <hi>juſt intereſt;</hi> to divert him, from accepting of that whereof he was am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious, and whereto he aſpired, whilſt he pretended the contrary, (though with ſome hazards to my ſelf, both in relation to him who well enough perceived my intention; and of my reputation alſo with many of them, who misjudged thereof) and to proſecute likewiſe, a means of my deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance from thoſe my <hi>perſonal Oppreſſions,</hi> whereof I ſtill have cauſe to complain. And (my Conſcience perſwading it was both lawful, and my duty to make tryal of that <hi>Power</hi>) I omitted no honeſt Courſe or Opportunity, to ſignifie my <hi>Grievances,</hi> that I might obtain remedy. But I laboured with no more ſucceſs, then if I had petitioned to the Dead: For neither by him who uſurped the <hi>Throne</hi> (though by many <hi>References</hi> he pretended to do me Juſtice) nor by any of his <hi>Aſſemblies</hi> called <hi>Parliaments,</hi> though I continually attended them; nor, by his <hi>Council,</hi> nor by his <hi>Succeſſour,</hi> could I procure ſo much toward the obtaining of <hi>common Juſtice,</hi> as to have one <hi>Petition</hi> taken into ſerious Conſideration; yea, though I was always faithful (as I think my ſelf bound in conſcience to be) to that <hi>Power</hi> which <hi>GOD</hi> permitteth for the time being, to reign o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us.</p>
               <p>Therefore, this <hi>Parliament,</hi> which he violently interrupted, being now again by <hi>GOD</hi>'s Mercy reſtored; and the <hi>Diſtractions</hi> and <hi>Neceſſities</hi> of this <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> rendring it ſo difficult as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, to get admittance for <hi>private Petitions,</hi> that I am yet without <hi>Relief,</hi> and likely to be quite deſtroyed as to my <hi>outward well-being,</hi> before this <hi>Parliament,</hi> will in the ordinary courſe, without ſome extraordinary means, take cognizance of my <hi>ſad Cauſe;</hi> I am reſolved by this <hi>Expedient,</hi> and the <hi>Preparatories,</hi> which I think therewith uſeful, to make tryal, once more for ever, whether or no, there be in this <hi>Nation</hi> (as <hi>I</hi> yet hope there is) that <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Mercy</hi> which eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>Governments,</hi> and which is likely to reſtore our loſt <hi>Liberties,</hi> and free us from <hi>preſent Burthens,</hi> and <hi>future Oppreſſions:</hi> And, this <hi>Tryal,</hi> if it prove but as effectual as my laſt <hi>Expedients,</hi> to the two late <hi>Protectors,</hi> preſented unto them a little before the death of the firſt, and the removal of the laſt, will ſhortly (though it produce not what I reaſonably expect) put an end at leaſt to thoſe vain hopes, which every day increaſe my <hi>Conſumption;</hi> and which have already, almoſt every way
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:116002:3"/>conſumed me, by long chargeable <hi>Sollicitations</hi> and numerous <hi>Petitions,</hi> hitherto taken into mens hands, and pockets, but not into their hearts.</p>
               <p>But, leſt my Petition, <hi>Narrative,</hi> and <hi>Preparatives</hi> afore-mentioned, which are the <hi>Foundation</hi> of this <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> may not herewith come to your hands; and ſo the true ſtate of my <hi>Caſe</hi> be to you, in ſome conſiderable Circumſtances unknown; I will here inſert a Copy of my <hi>Petition</hi> inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to this <hi>Parliament.</hi>
               </p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="petition">
                  <body>
                     <head>To the PARLIAMENT of the COMMONWEALTH of <hi>England:</hi>
                     </head>
                     <head type="sub">The Humble Petition of <hi>Geo. Wither</hi> Eſq;</head>
                     <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
                     <p>THat, this <hi>Petitioners Demands</hi> and <hi>Accompts</hi> being ſtated upon Oath by the <hi>Committee</hi> for Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they were afterward re-examined (a trouble rarely (if ever) impoſed upon any other) by two <hi>Committees of Parliament</hi> ſucceſſively, (to wit) the <hi>Committee of the Navy,</hi> and a <hi>Select Committee.</hi> The ſaid <hi>Committee of the Navy,</hi> reported by <hi>Col. Thompſon,</hi> that, <hi>3438 l. 18 s. 4 d.</hi> was then due to this Petitioner, beſide ſome Demands then reſpited.</p>
                     <p>That <hi>Report,</hi> not being brought into the <hi>Houſe</hi> until about ſix months after (in which time, the beſt part of a <hi>million</hi> was, to this Petitioners damage charged in <hi>Courſe</hi> before it) the ſum of <hi>1681 l. 15 s. 8 d. &amp;c.</hi> part of the ſaid <hi>3438 l.</hi> was charged upon the <hi>Exciſe in Courſe, March 22. 1647.</hi> but, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out allowance of any <hi>Intereſt,</hi> though <hi>700 l.</hi> thereof (for which this <hi>Petitioner</hi> paid intereſt) was by him, ingaged for, and disburſed for the <hi>State;</hi> and though likewiſe, the reſt of the ſaid <hi>1681 l.</hi> was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo made immediately payable unto him, by <hi>Warrants</hi> or <hi>Orders</hi> about four years before, and due for <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice</hi> under the ſame <hi>Commander,</hi> at the ſame times, and in the ſame places, for which his <hi>fellow-ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers</hi> had either preſent payment in ready money, or intereſt allowed.</p>
                     <p>This, being made evident, it was ordered <hi>Decemb. 25. 1648,</hi> that <hi>300 l.</hi> more ſhould be charged up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Exciſe,</hi> in conſideration of Expences and <hi>Intereſt</hi> before that day laid out, for the ſaid <hi>700 l.</hi> and that Intereſt of <hi>8 l. per Cent.</hi> ſhould be paid every ſix <hi>months,</hi> both for the ſaid <hi>300 l.</hi> and <hi>700 l.</hi> out of the Exciſe alſo, from that time, until the ſaid <hi>300 l.</hi> and <hi>700 l.</hi> ſhould be diſcharged. To this <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> the Concurrence of the <hi>Lords</hi> was deſired; but about a week after, and before that Concurrence could be obtained, this <hi>Parliament</hi> took away the <hi>Houſe of Lords,</hi> and this Petitioner could never af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter get <hi>Principal</hi> or <hi>Intereſt,</hi> or the ſaid Order to be allowed.</p>
                     <p>The remainder of the ſaid <hi>3438 l.</hi> was the ſame <hi>March 1647.</hi> made payable out of diſcoveries at <hi>Haberdaſhers-Hall,</hi> and afterward by another <hi>Order</hi> out of <hi>Compoſitions</hi> at <hi>Goldſmiths-Hall;</hi> which not being effectual, this <hi>Petitioner</hi> after many tedious and chargeable <hi>Sollicitations,</hi> petitioned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; and then <hi>this Parliament</hi> referred the <hi>whole Cauſe,</hi> and the finding out means for this <hi>Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> ſatisfaction, to the ſaid <hi>Select Committee,</hi> who found <hi>3958 l. 15 s. 8 d.</hi> to be then due, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, that they thought fit, it ſhould be thus paid, <hi>(viz.)</hi> that the ſaid <hi>1681 l.</hi> ſhould ſtand charged upon the Exciſe as formerly; and that intereſt ſhould be paid for that whole ſum (as in equity it ought) after the rate aforeſaid, from the <hi>22</hi> of <hi>Septemb.</hi> then laſt paſt, until the <hi>Principal</hi> were paid; and that for the reſt of the ſaid <hi>3958 l. 15 s. 8 d.</hi> there ſhould be ſettled upon this Petitioner and his heirs, Lands by them nominated, as they were valued in the <hi>Sequeſtrators</hi> Books, whoſe yearly valuation was <hi>240 l.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>No Reſult appearing upon this <hi>Report</hi> in a long time after, this Petitioner once again petitioned, and upon the <hi>2</hi> of <hi>January 1650,</hi> inſtead of the ſatisfaction laſt mentioned, it was ordered, that the ſaid <hi>1681 l. 15 s. 8 d.</hi> part of the ſaid <hi>3958 l.</hi> ſhould ſtand charged upon the <hi>Exoiſe</hi> as before, but without mentioning any intereſt, whether intended or not: if not intended, then both the <hi>money lent,</hi> and the <hi>reſidue</hi> having been due above <hi>16</hi> years, yet payable but in <hi>Courſe,</hi> which hath been ſtopped above ſeven years, (without any certain termination of the ſaid <hi>ſtop</hi>) is likely to be a <hi>payment</hi> amounting to many thouſand pounds leſs then nothing; and the <hi>payment</hi> which the <hi>Petitioner</hi> hath for the <hi>Remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> is worſe.</p>
                     <p>For, by the ſame <hi>Order,</hi> inſtead of <hi>240 l. per an.</hi> according to what the ſaid ſelect Committee though
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116002:4"/>ſonable, he was to have but <hi>150 l. per annum</hi> ſettled upon him the ſaid Petitioner, out of the Eſtate of <hi>Jo. Denham</hi> Eſq; for ſatisfaction of the remainder, of the ſaid <hi>3958 l.</hi> which Lands (all things conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) he was to pay for, at <hi>40</hi> years purchaſe in ready money, whereas he could have bought for leſs then eight years, the like Lands; yet, this Petitioner accepted thereof, and had the ſaid <hi>150 l. per annum,</hi> conveyed unto him out of the Mannor of <hi>Little Horſly</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> part of the Eſtate of the ſaid <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and purchaſed the reſt of the ſaid Mannor for <hi>1645 l.</hi> and odde money; paid for it, according to his <hi>contract,</hi> and was put into quiet poſſeſſion.</p>
                     <p>But, whilſt he was in poſſeſſion, he made not one penny of clear profit, by reaſon of interruptions; and hath now been ejected about five years out of the whole Mannor, without either Rent or Recompence, and hath ſpent alſo about <hi>600 l.</hi> in troubles and ſuits yet undetermined, to defend and recover his Title; which Suits were occaſioned by a pretended <hi>Leaſe</hi> to one <hi>Thomas Offly</hi> Eſq; which is probably forged, to the defrauding the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> of between <hi>3</hi> or <hi>4000 l.</hi> and the ſaid Leaſe, if it be real, was at a great undervalue, compounded for by a Member of this <hi>Parliament,</hi> to the wrong of the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> as well as of this Petitioner, as will appear by the <hi>Narrative</hi> hereto annexed, and by what this Petitioner ſhall further demonſtrate. By theſe procceedings, this <hi>Petitioner</hi> is damnified ſo much, beſide his trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and the loſs of precious time at the latter end of his life, that he proteſteth in the fear of GOD, he is in danger with his whole Family to be ruined in his <hi>Eſtate</hi> and <hi>Credit,</hi> and that he verily believeth, he had been about <hi>5000 l.</hi> better in his Eſtate, if he had quitted the ſaid <hi>3958 l. 15 s. 8 d.</hi> when it was firſt due.</p>
                     <p>This <hi>Petitioner</hi> further ſheweth, that about eight years paſt he purchaſed of the <hi>State</hi> a ſmall parcel of Land at <hi>Aſh</hi> in <hi>Surry,</hi> whereof he is totally deprived alſo, by a <hi>Member</hi> of this <hi>Parliament,</hi> who hath ever ſince detained the ſaid <hi>Land</hi> and <hi>Rent</hi> from him; and who having been often ſummoned by the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners</hi> for <hi>removing of Obſtructions,</hi> to ſhew his <hi>Title,</hi> refuſeth or neglecteth ſo to do; and this <hi>Petitioner</hi> being not able to commence a ſuit for it, is likely for ever to loſe both his ſaid <hi>purchaſe,</hi> and what be paid for it, unleſs the ſaid <hi>Member</hi> may be ordered, to do that which is agreeable to <hi>Juſtice;</hi> which he humbly deſireth he may be compelled to do.</p>
                     <p>And, in Conſideration of the reſt of the <hi>Premiſes,</hi> this <hi>Petitioner</hi> humbly prayes alſo, that the <hi>Requeſts</hi> at the Cloſe of the ſaid <hi>Narrative</hi> hereto annexed, may be granted, ſo far forth as they are juſt; and that your <hi>Honours</hi> will put ſuch a ſpeedy end, to his ſaid <hi>Grievances,</hi> that he may die in <hi>Peace:</hi> For he will be contented with whatſoever you ſhall determine, and pray for your Honours.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Let, not this be ſlighted; for my life is worn out by <hi>Oppreſſions,</hi> (the 70 year of my <hi>Age</hi> being paſt) and, you may perceive by the preceding <hi>Petition</hi> and the <hi>Narrative,</hi> that this <hi>Parliament</hi> before the interruption thereof, (by the prevalency of ſome among them, and now juſtly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded) as alſo by their <hi>Interruptors,</hi> in delay of <hi>Justice,</hi> have cauſed me to be damnified in at leaſt 8000 <hi>l.</hi> by detaining a very conſiderable part of my <hi>Eſtate</hi> above ſixteen years, and by not making good their <hi>Contracts and Engagements,</hi> wherein I conſided; and whereby (as I believe) there hath been caſt upon me more then 40 times the <hi>Burthen</hi> juſtly impoſed upon any man of my <hi>Revenue:</hi> which (conſidering how ſerviceable I have been without conſtraint, in adventuring my life, and contributing my <hi>Eſtate</hi> with the firſt, in order to a preſervation of <hi>Common-Right</hi> and <hi>Safety</hi>) hath been an unequal diſtribution; and reduced me to ſuch <hi>Extremities,</hi> as I expected not to be plunged into by <hi>Friends,</hi> who have been ſo merciful to their <hi>Enemies;</hi> and who made pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of better things; for, they were ſuch <hi>Hardſhips,</hi> as I could other while hardly brook; and ſuch, as if my greateſt <hi>Adverſary</hi> had been in the like caſe, I ſhould have afforded him more pity then I have found. This, I profeſs without falſhood or equivocation, for, I have had dayly vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations thereby; and at ſometimes been ſo afflicted, with <hi>ſhame</hi> and <hi>grief,</hi> when I thereby failed their expectations, who confided upon my Credit, and my <hi>Engagements</hi> to them, that it made my <hi>life</hi> weariſome, (eſpecially when they were neceſſitous perſons) until I could finde means to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply their need, how much ſoever it were to my diſadvantage. To preſerve my ſelf, as much as I could from this vexation and ſcandal, and to ſupply my perſonal wants, (occaſioned by other mens deceiving my hopes) I have been enforced to fell away lately above 2000 <hi>l.</hi> worth of my
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116002:4"/>then remaining <hi>Livelyhood, real and perſonal;</hi> and am ſtill engaged by my <hi>continuing Oppreſſions,</hi> in almoſt as much more, though I have ſince the ſales laſt mentioned, ſold by parcels, to the diſmem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring of my Inheritance, all that was diſengaged, and at my <hi>free diſpoſe:</hi> yet the <hi>Conſumption</hi> goes on; inſomuch that the <hi>remainder</hi> of the <hi>portion</hi> left in poſſeſſion, (unleſs part of that which is due to me may be paid, to free it from <hi>Incumbrances</hi>) is likely to be forfeited within a few months. And, though that <hi>Forfeiture</hi> ſhould be ſaved, my <hi>Revenue</hi> will not be ſufficient to diſcharge <hi>Taxes</hi> and <hi>Parochial Payments,</hi> with the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of my <hi>remaining debts,</hi> and inavoydable Expences by them annually occaſioned, (without a further ſupply out of what is detained from me) &amp; afford a main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance for my <hi>ſelf,</hi> my <hi>wife, children</hi> and <hi>ſervants,</hi> (though a far leſs number then heretofore) after the rate of 5 <hi>s.</hi> the week one perſon with another throughout the year, to provide <hi>meat, drink, rayment, ſervants wages, childrens portions,</hi> and all other neceſſaries in ſickneſs and in health.</p>
               <p>And leſs I ſhould have had (as rich as the world thinks me) if my <hi>frugality</hi> (which hath been reputed a parſimony to my diſparagement) had not been many years rather proportioned to my <hi>weak Eſtate,</hi> then to the <hi>rank in which I lived:</hi> For, I ſhall ſhortly be in danger, to have neither <hi>Stock</hi> upon my <hi>Land,</hi> nor <hi>Goods</hi> in my <hi>Houſe,</hi> nor a <hi>Houſe</hi> wherein to hide my head, except it be a <hi>Priſon,</hi> if my <hi>Creditors</hi> be not more merciful by forbearance, till I can make money of what is yet left, then my Debters have been to enfore me to that hazard: who, (if I had been juſtly dealt withal) ſhould probably have long ſince poſſeſſed a <hi>Revenue</hi> of above 500 <hi>l. per annum,</hi> free from <hi>Debts</hi> and <hi>Engagements,</hi> and might have raiſed alſo 5000 <hi>l.</hi> for my <hi>Childrens portions,</hi> who have yet nothing. And, which is worſe then <hi>ſo bad;</hi> I, whoſe <hi>Credit</hi> was ſo good, that when occaſion here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore required it, I have borrowed 100. 200. 300 <hi>l.</hi> yea, 600 <hi>l.</hi> in one place for ſeveral years upon my <hi>ſingle bond,</hi> (as will yet appear by the bonds cancelled) am now doubtful whether my ſecurity will paſs alone for 10 <hi>l.</hi> And, I believe, that they who (perhaps to diſparage me in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kinde) report I have <hi>Lands</hi> to the yearly value of 1000 <hi>l.</hi> (which is a great deal more then twice ſo much as I ever yet had) will not better my credit by that fame, as to borrowing at this time: and though it do not, <hi>Poverty,</hi> when the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> is poor, will to me be more honour, then to be <hi>rich;</hi> conſidering how I am impoveriſhed.</p>
               <p>Not many men have ſo unfeignedly told the <hi>world</hi> heretofore, their <hi>outward Condition,</hi> as I have declared mine, when it was requiſite; nor diſcovered their <hi>inſide</hi> more ſincerely, by publiſhing their thoughts, to his own hazard, for an advantage to his <hi>Country:</hi> But moſt are ſuch diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blers, that they believe not one another. If men think I now <hi>diſſemble,</hi> and am as rich as <hi>report</hi> hath made me, perhaps whilſt I am here at <hi>London</hi> ſolliciting my Cauſe, they will ſteal away my <hi>onely Son and Daughter,</hi> in hope they will prove rich <hi>marriages:</hi> which <hi>nevertheleſs</hi> I am reſolved to <hi>adventure;</hi> as alſo, how the <hi>Militia</hi> in <hi>Hamſhire,</hi> out of which I am by <hi>Providence</hi> (if not by ſome other <hi>means</hi> omitted) will <hi>proportion</hi> my <hi>burthen</hi> to other <hi>mens.</hi> I hope well of their impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality; but, if (as I am <hi>informed</hi>) they have impoſed upon me the <hi>ſetting</hi> forth of <hi>two Horſes,</hi> I ſhall be ſcarce found able at this time to provide them <hi>Bridles;</hi> and ſome of my <hi>Country-men</hi> may as juſtly be charged with a whole <hi>Troop:</hi> according to which <hi>proportion,</hi> if a <hi>Militia</hi> be armed <hi>in</hi> all other <hi>Counties, Charles Stuart,</hi> were better ſtay at <hi>Bruxells,</hi> then come hither, though <hi>Spain, France,</hi> and the <hi>Emperour</hi> ſhould aſſiſt him.</p>
               <p>How this revealing of my <hi>Poverty</hi> will obſtruct my <hi>Credit,</hi> as to <hi>borrowing</hi> hereafter to relieve my neceſſities; and how it may hinder the advance of my <hi>Children</hi> in <hi>Marriage,</hi> the prudence of the world, would have adviſed me to conſider. But I regard neither her Counſel nor her Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe: If <hi>Marriages,</hi> according to our <hi>Proverb,</hi> be made in Heaven; and, if (as I believe, and have had experience of it) good <hi>Husbands</hi> and <hi>Wives,</hi> are Gods gift, and at his diſpoſal by an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary <hi>Providence,</hi> I will truſt to his providing them <hi>Spouſes</hi> and <hi>Portions:</hi> and whatſoever my future <hi>want</hi> ſhall be, do purpoſe to deceive <hi>no man,</hi> by making my <hi>Eſtate</hi> ſeem better then it is; though they be not of that <hi>minde,</hi> who obſtruct the eſtabliſhing of <hi>Regiſters</hi> to <hi>prevent fraud.</hi> When I was much poorer then at <hi>preſent</hi> I am, GOD, raiſed me up a <hi>Friend,</hi> who knowing by what <hi>means</hi> I was neceſſitated, (and how unlikely I was to repay him) brought nevertheleſs unto me with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out my asking ought, (without obliging me by a <hi>note under my hand,</hi> and without ſo much as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring a <hi>promiſe of repayment</hi>) 500 <hi>l.</hi> by parcels, at ſeveral times, during the continuance of my
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116002:5"/>
                  <hi>wants;</hi> And the ſame GOD, who thereunto inclined him, without any earthly relation, is my GOD at this day, and will be ſo for ever.</p>
               <p>Herein conſiſts that which keeps up my <hi>spirit,</hi> at this preſent, notwithſtanding the long neglect of my <hi>Oppreſſions,</hi> and the <hi>Wants,</hi> it hath brought upon me; and though the Parliaments late lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving me out of <hi>Publick Employments,</hi> hath occaſioned me to be ſuſpected by their <hi>Friends,</hi> as not well-affected thereunto; to be he laughed at by the <hi>Commonwealths open Enemies,</hi> and as much hated as heretofore, becauſe they well enough know my continuing faithfulneſs to her <hi>Intereſt:</hi> Though it may cauſe me to be <hi>jeered by Newters;</hi> to be <hi>ſlighted</hi> by my <hi>debauched Neighbours;</hi> to be the ſooner ſtript of what is yet left, by <hi>Creditors</hi> and <hi>Publicans;</hi> and to be made lyable to the fury of every <hi>Armed-party,</hi> into whoſe hands I may poſſibly fall during theſe times of <hi>Inſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction;</hi> notwithſtanding all this, now likely to come upon me, I neither diſtruſtfully repine at what I ſuffer, (though I uſe the beſt means I can to remove it) nor fear what may come hereafter, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe GOD is my <hi>Refuge.</hi> If it were not ſo, which way ſhould I turn my ſelf to find comfort? My <hi>Eſtate</hi> is like a <hi>Candle</hi> burnt within the <hi>Socket:</hi> Age hath ſomewhat abated my ſtrength: <hi>Friends</hi> and <hi>Acquaintance</hi> (like ſuch as <hi>Poverty</hi> produceth) <hi>ſtand afar off:</hi> my <hi>Comforters,</hi> are like <hi>Job</hi>'s: my <hi>Enemies</hi> are malitious, and increaſe: my <hi>deareſt Relations,</hi> have nothing to contribute but <hi>Téars</hi> or <hi>Complaints</hi> to the afflicting of my heart with unprofitable pity: and though I have looked for Helpers, not one appears, but He who never fails thoſe that truſt in him; and he alſo otherwhile hides himſelf, becauſe of my <hi>tranſgreſſions,</hi> till I am ready to cry out, <hi>Oh God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> and then he diſcovers himſelf again, and ſmiles on me. But, what is this to the world? though he be ſo gracious, that I have no cauſe to murmur at his permitting me to be harſhly uſed, nor do repine at that permiſſion; I will nevertheleſs not forbear to declare how the world deals with me, though ſhe calls it murmuring.</p>
               <p>But, ſome will perhaps object, that <hi>I</hi> cannot be ſo neceſſitated as <hi>I</hi> pretend; for it is evident that <hi>I</hi> have ſuch and ſuch a viſible <hi>Eſtate. I</hi> confeſs, <hi>I</hi> have an <hi>Eſtate</hi> viſible afar off, partly in Reverſion, and partly incumbred; but, it is not <hi>Tangible,</hi> as to my neceſſary occaſions. Like <hi>Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talus, I</hi> have an appearance of food at my upper lip, and water to the Chinne, but not in poſſeſſion more then <hi>I</hi> have declared; and thoſe falſe appearances of plenty, make them who know not how it is really with me, and know how long <hi>I</hi> have ſubſiſted in a ſeeming good condition ſince <hi>I</hi> had cauſe to complain, think me a <hi>male-contented murmurer,</hi> (which is none of the leaſt <hi>disparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi>) rather juſtly reprovable for complaining, without need, then to be pitied; which <hi>Unchriſtian prejudice,</hi> hath not a little encreaſed the Cauſe, and prolonged the juſtneſs of my <hi>complaints. I</hi> have yet, a <hi>viſible Eſtate;</hi> but a great part of it lies like an <hi>Orphans</hi> portion in the hands of a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful unconſcionable <hi>Guardian,</hi> who makes uſe of it for his own occaſions; and leaves him to beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery and ſtarving. The Reſidue of my <hi>Livelyhood, I</hi> poſſeſs as <hi>Bees</hi> do their honey, when the Combs &amp; Cells are ſo broken and maſht together in the Hive, (which ſtandeth ſound in outward view) that inſtead of being nouriſhed by it, they lye intangled, and ſprawling out their lives, ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered in the midſt of their plenty; and am in a worſe condition then the poor perfecuted Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants in <hi>Piedmont,</hi> and other places, for whoſe relief <hi>Contributions</hi> were of late largely and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably made, (pray GOD they were as ſincerely diſpoſed of) yet <hi>I</hi> am likely to be ere long in a more ſad eſtate: for, they being driven from all they had, by their Enemies, retained their <hi>Liberty,</hi> which <hi>I</hi> am likely to loſe; they had their reputation increaſed by ſuffering for their <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and ſome Friends alſo to relieve them; whereas <hi>I</hi> am ruined in my <hi>Eſtate</hi> and <hi>Credit,</hi> by and among thoſe whom <hi>I</hi> thought my <hi>Friends:</hi> and what ſuccour are <hi>my Averſaries</hi> to whom <hi>I</hi> am expoſed, likely to afford me? or, to whom ſhall I complain? There is a <hi>Catholick Congregation,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>I</hi> am a Member, among whom there is true compaſſion; but, they are perſonally as unknown to me, as the 7000 in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who had not bowed their knees to <hi>Baal,</hi> were to <hi>Elias,</hi> who knew not one of that number. <hi>I</hi> have onely a ſpiritual <hi>Communion</hi> with them, and my ſupplies from them, will be rather in ſpiritual <hi>Communications,</hi> then in <hi>temporal things,</hi> wherewith <hi>I</hi> ſhall be well enough contented. <hi>The earth is the LORDS, and all that is therein,</hi> upon whoſe ſcore <hi>I</hi> ſhall expect what is neceſſary for life, if all were loſt; and for the ſervices which <hi>I</hi> have heretofore done for my Country, and for the love <hi>I</hi> ſtill bear to it, <hi>I</hi> may claim ſo much at leaſt, as due to me of right, though it had paid me all the debt it owes me, and though <hi>I</hi> had loſt it another way.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:116002:5"/>
               <p>That which moſt afflicts me, is not altogether the damage which I outwardly ſubſtain in having the adventuring my <hi>life and eſtate</hi> for this <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> ſo little regarded; nor the ſhameful <hi>poverty</hi> that I have been expoſed unto, by thoſe who have more cauſe to be aſhamed of it then I: But the diſhonour and hazards which are brought upon this <hi>Nation</hi> and their <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative,</hi> by ſuch like neglects of <hi>Juſtice</hi> as have occaſioned my complaints, and our univerſal hazard, is my greateſt grief; ſeeing, to my knowledge, they might have been prevented with a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle coſt and trouble, if ſome had not wilfully obſtructed, or neglected <hi>Juſtice,</hi> for ſiniſter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects. The mony, which hath been owing to me above 16. years, might have been paid 16. times in that ſpace, out of treaſure disburſed much leſs for the Publick honour and profit. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, the <hi>Lands</hi> of 300 <hi>li.</hi> yearly value by me purchaſed of the <hi>State,</hi> and fully paid for ſeven years paſt, and yet ſtill detained from me, (without having received one peny in clear profit, or any allowance for that damage, beſide the loſs of 500 <hi>li.</hi> more conſumed in vain to defend my poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and recover it being loſt, by a pretented <hi>Mortgage,</hi> which is probably forged) might have been re-eſtabliſhed upon me long ſince, if the ſaid <hi>Mortgage</hi> had not been unduely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded for by a <hi>Member of Parliament;</hi> or if the validity of his <hi>Title,</hi> might have been examin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, together with ſuch actings relating thereto, as do ſeem to have been practiſed to defraud the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> of between 3. and 4000 <hi>li.</hi> as well as to deprive me of that <hi>Revenue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe things, I declare not, to aſperſe the Parliament, who could not help them, whilſt their power was interrupted; but, to prevent the diſhonouring thereof, now that power is reſtored: and ſo far I am from intending otherwiſe, that I think none but an Enemy thereunto, will ſo miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>underſtand me, though ſome among them were guilty; Seeing, the defects by unſound <hi>Limbs</hi> can be no more diſreputation thereto, then it was to the twelve Diſciples, that there was a Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor among them; or, then it is to a man, otherwiſe well qualified, to be born with a <hi>crooked mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> or to have a <hi>ſcab</hi> upon his body by caſual Infection, which he endeavours to be rid of, as ſoon as he knows it. Nor doth my inſiſting upon the particulars aforementioned, proceed out of deſpair that I ſhall be left quite deſtitute, of things neceſſary to life: For, GOD, who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for me when I was moſt deſerted of the world, as I have already declared, aſſures me of the like mercy hereafter: Nor, do I thus diſcover my <hi>nakedneſs</hi> and ſordid <hi>poverty,</hi> in hope to move compaſſion, by my own endeavour only; or when my own time requires it: For, I am not ſuch a ſtranger to this <hi>Generation,</hi> and to the temper of moſt men therein, as not to know, that this <hi>Diſcovery</hi> (unleſs GOD reſtrain them, or change their minds) will expoſe me to the more miſery and contempt; and give men encouragement to tread me over head and ears into the durt, rather then to relieve me, or raiſe me up, when they ſee me ſinking.</p>
               <p>Therefore, that which I have now written, and heretofore expreſſed to the like effects, is not wholly for the foreſaid cauſes; but partly, to diſcharge my <hi>Conſcience,</hi> in uſing that, which was wont to be the ordinary or extraordinary means of redreſſing <hi>Oppreſſions;</hi> and partly, that if they ſucceeded not, I might leave an <hi>experiment</hi> to them who ſhall live when I am dead, that there was a time, and may be again, wherein <hi>Hypocriſie, Apoſtacy, Avarice, Pride, Selfneſs,</hi> and <hi>hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heartedneſs,</hi> ſo abounded, that no <hi>words</hi> would move; no <hi>demonſtrations</hi> perſwade, no endeavour pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a reaſonable or natural conſequence; but, that the more rationally, the more evidently, an <hi>oppreſſed man</hi> ſhall make known his <hi>oppreſſions,</hi> and an <hi>innocent,</hi> vindicate his <hi>innocency,</hi> the more ſhall they neglect his ſufferings; and the more maliciouſly, the more impudently practice to diſgrace and fruſtrate his juſtification: And I have alſo written this, that conſidering there be <hi>times,</hi> and <hi>Contingencies,</hi> wherein, and whereby, <hi>The Race is not to the ſwift, nor the Battel to the strong, nor Bread to the wiſe, nor Riches to men of understanding;</hi> ſome, thereby, may heed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, to repoſe <hi>Truſt,</hi> not in themſelves, or in <hi>Princes,</hi> or in <hi>Parliaments,</hi> or in <hi>Armies,</hi> or in the <hi>People,</hi> or in any other ſave in GOD, only.</p>
               <p>But, <hi>Non vacat exiguis rebus adeſſe Jovi,</hi> our Terreſtrial GODS, have now work enough to ſecure themſelves, and to look to the <hi>common ſafety:</hi> and therefore, ſome ſeem to think it cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal to offer a <hi>private grievance,</hi> at this time, to be redreſſed by them, how deſtructive ſoever it be. Theſe men, having never felt ſuch <hi>oppreſſions</hi> as mine, nor wanted any thing neceſſary, theſe do, inſtead of a <hi>charitable aſſiſtance,</hi> or fellow feeling of my ſufferings when they hear them
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116002:6"/>declared, tell me, that ſuch <hi>complainings</hi> may be of dangerous conſequence; that they are ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptoms of a diſcontented minde; and that I muſt be patient. <hi>Good Lord! how wiſe they are?</hi> why do they not reprove and blame all the <hi>Saints</hi> in Primitive Ages, as impatient and male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented perſons, becauſe frequent in complainings againſt their Oppreſſors? why do they not counſel thoſe who are like to ſtarve, through want of bread, not to be <hi>hungry?</hi> and thoſe who are ſick and wounded, not to be ſenſible of <hi>pain?</hi> how zealous of the <hi>Common-peace</hi> are they, who never contributed any thing toward the preſervation of it, except <hi>words,</hi> which coſt them nothing? If I had contributed and adventured no more, I ſhould not have needed their grave <hi>advice</hi> or <hi>reproof</hi> at this time, but ſhould have been thought as <hi>wiſe</hi> as they, and might perhaps had as little cauſe to complain. There be ſome, who are never ſenſible of other mens dangers or loſſes, till they themſelves are likely to be impoveriſhed or deſtroyed; other ſome there be, who never get any thing, until all is in hazard to be loſt; and if I am deſtined to ſuch a <hi>Lot,</hi> a time ſo buſie, and hazardous as this, may be the moſt ſeaſonable time for preferring my <hi>Petition,</hi> though it appear unſeaſonable to ſome: for, I am not ſo irrational, to deſire more then may be granted, or to expect a full <hi>repair;</hi> but rather, that ſo much time only may be ſpared, as will ſuffice to <hi>order</hi> a ſupply for thoſe <hi>Wants</hi> which cannot longer be born; and a ſtop ſet to thoſe <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings</hi> which will be deſtructive, before a more ample <hi>proviſion</hi> may be made.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Parliament,</hi> I confeſs, hath now little <hi>leaſure,</hi> and leſs then at any time heretofore, wherein <hi>Private Grievances,</hi> were put off by former <hi>Aſſemblies:</hi> yet I know it hath not ſo little <hi>leaſure,</hi> as not to ſpare half an hour, to the charitable purpoſe laſt mentioned. The <hi>common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafety,</hi> is viſibly in danger; But, I hope not ſo indangered, that it is diſenabled from! doing ſuch a <hi>work</hi> of <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Mercy,</hi> as may prevent an increaſe of their own diſhonour, dangers, and expences. The <hi>Commonwealth</hi> is in great <hi>want;</hi> but, their wants will be greater before they will become leſs, if (as in my Caſe) <hi>Juſtice</hi> be deferred to the doubling or trebling of their debts, by leaving thoſe things unexamined (until <hi>Witneſſes</hi> are dead, or <hi>Evidences</hi> embezzelled) which might probably diſcharge the greateſt part of them, by timely recovery of that which will elſe be loſt. I was delayed as I now am, by every <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> in being, during the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruption of this <hi>Parliament,</hi> with this <hi>Anſwer: The Publick affairs afford not leaſure:</hi> But, who believ'd it? Nay, who believed not the contrary, that obſerved, as I did, for what things they found <hi>leaſure? Leaſure,</hi> was often found ſince I firſt petitioned (though I cannot ſay it of my certain knowledge ſince this <hi>Parliaments reſtauration</hi>) to hear <hi>private</hi> Complaints, far leſs conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable then mine, on the behalf of <hi>themſelves, friends, kinſmen,</hi> and other <hi>relations,</hi> even du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thoſe <hi>Weeks and Moneths,</hi> wherein <hi>private Petitions,</hi> were excluded by <hi>Order</hi> of the <hi>Houſe;</hi> as if ſuch <hi>Orders</hi> had been only purpoſed, to give them the more caſie admittance. O God! why am I neceſſitated to bring to remembrance, <hi>miſactings,</hi> whereby thou haſt been provoked, and thy ſervants exaſperated? <hi>Leaſure,</hi> hath been found for <hi>Malefactors,</hi> when it concerned but their <hi>Eſtates</hi> or <hi>Lives</hi> only; And why could not leaſure have been as well afforded in ſo many years, to preſerve my <hi>Eſtate,</hi> and my <hi>Credit,</hi> which I more value then <hi>Life;</hi> and for preſervation where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, I would have given my <hi>eſtate,</hi> and two <hi>temporary Lives</hi> to boot, if I had them? <hi>Leaſure,</hi> hath been found, to qualifie rigid proceedings againſt the <hi>Commonwealths Adverſaries;</hi> yea, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodate them; nay, to ingratiate them; and <hi>leaſure,</hi> is found ſtill to the like purpoſes; which I grumble not at in reſpect of them: But, why might not I as well in all that time, have obtained ſuch favour? why might not ſuch a day or hour of <hi>leaſure</hi> be found out for me? why might not I, who have been Inſtrumental for this <hi>Republicks</hi> preſervation, have been as much befriended as her <hi>Enemies,</hi> who ſought to deſtroy it? but becauſe the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> and her <hi>Servants,</hi> have not ſuch diligent friends as their <hi>Enemies?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh God! remember not this <hi>negligence</hi> and <hi>partiality</hi> to the <hi>Publick</hi> diſadvantage at this time, wherein <hi>faithful friends,</hi> and <hi>truſty ſervants,</hi> are as needfull as ever they were. Theſe are the <hi>Provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations,</hi> which have made their <hi>leaſure,</hi> ſo little, and their buſineſs to be ſo much, ſtill multiply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe <hi>troubles,</hi> which increaſe their expences, and ſtreightning them in time: and, the more they labour, and the more mony they beſtow, the more will their <hi>work,</hi> and <hi>disburſements</hi> be, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til thoſe things which occaſion it be reformed; and, if there be any one in that <hi>honourable Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly,</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:116002:6"/>who believes not this; or, who is not ſo much humbled, for the failings which have been here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore among them, that he can be willing to hear them mentioned for prevention of the like, (by him who deſires the preſervation of their Power with honour) I ſhall be more afraid of the diſſervice that ſuch a <hi>Member</hi> may do to <hi>GOD,</hi> and to his <hi>Country,</hi> then of his diſpleaſure, or of any miſchief that can thereby befal me; and therefore, having ſaid what I think, concerning the <hi>Leaſure,</hi> which they heretofore had in <hi>Parliament,</hi> to take more Cognizance of <hi>private Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances,</hi> I will adde ſomewhat in anſwer to their <hi>Allegation,</hi> who ſay, <hi>Publick Neceſſities,</hi> make the Parliament uncapable of relieving mine; and that, I ought not at this time to petition for it, but rather to reſt ſatisfied.</p>
               <p>This, is as diſſatisfactory to me, as it would be to my <hi>Creditors,</hi> when they are like to be undone by want of their money, if I ſhould tell them, my neceſſities are ſo great that <hi>I</hi> cannot pay them, and that therefore they muſt reſt ſatisfied; though they ſaw at that time, in and about my houſe, many unneceſſary things, which were more chargeable then profitable; by the ſale whereof, <hi>I</hi> might eaſily pay them all, and live as well contented, and with more, or with as much <hi>Credit</hi> as without them. Doubtleſs, my <hi>Creditors,</hi> if it were ſo with me, would expect a more <hi>ſatisfactory anſwer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In, like manner, <hi>I</hi> knowing the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> hath ſome <hi>Appurtenances,</hi> not ſo neceſſary as chargeable, and many things diſpoſable, whereby my <hi>Grievances</hi> may be eaſed, and my <hi>Credit</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, without any diſadvantage thereunto, cannot be well pleaſed with ſuch a <hi>Put-off,</hi> as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps <hi>I</hi> might have been, if <hi>I</hi> had lived theſe laſt 16 years (as <hi>I</hi> deſired to have done, and yet do) by a <hi>Woods ſide</hi> in a <hi>Country Village,</hi> where <hi>I</hi> had been kept without knowledge of what is done in <hi>Committees, Courts, Councils</hi> and <hi>Parliaments.</hi> Why, muſt a greater burthen then <hi>I</hi> am able to bear, or then falls to my <hi>proportion,</hi> be laid upon my back to uphold that which is <hi>falling?</hi> or to ſtop that <hi>Breach,</hi> whereby all the people of theſe three <hi>Nations,</hi> are liable to an inundation? Why ſhould it not be rather equally divided among them; or among thoſe who are beſt able to ſuſtain it, until ſuch an <hi>equal Diviſion</hi> could be made, rather then that ſo much ſhould be caſt upon me, or upon any other, as will deſtroy him? What juſtice is there ſuitable to our <hi>Chriſtian profeſſions,</hi> or to the <hi>mercies</hi> which GOD hath vouchſafed to this <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> to do otherwiſe? Or how much differs this <hi>partial diſtribution</hi> whereof I complain, from what was barbarouſly practiſed among the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles of old, when they ſacrificed <hi>innocent perſons</hi> to their <hi>falſe gods,</hi> that their <hi>wind-bound Fleets,</hi> (as did the <hi>Grecians</hi>) might have proſperous Gales? And, why was this <hi>Generation</hi> ſo imprudent, to requite me with <hi>evil</hi> for <hi>good,</hi> in ſo extraordinary a manner, as they have done, who have been a diligent Obſerver of what they have done? and who, am as ſenſible of Courteſies and Diſcourte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies, as other men? And alſo, better able to illuſtrate it when I am ſcurvily and unjuſtly dealt withal, then ſome <hi>wiſer men,</hi> or then many thouſands of other oppreſſed <hi>Suppliants,</hi> who have cauſe to complain? Why had it not more care of its own honour, though no regard of <hi>my Credit,</hi> to uſe me thus, conſidering <hi>I</hi> have ſome advantages on my ſide, whereby it will redound more to their ſhame, then the like <hi>Injustice</hi> to many hundreds of them, whoſe <hi>Obſcurity</hi> makes their <hi>Sufferings</hi> leſs heeded, and ſooner forgotten? If <hi>I,</hi> have thus ſuffered who had theſe advantages; who am known to the greateſt number of the moſt conſiderable perſons in the <hi>Nation;</hi> who have had familiarity with many of them, not without ſome appearances of good reſpect; who was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the greateſt number of <hi>Parliament Members,</hi> &amp; had many among them who profeſſed to be my <hi>Friends;</hi> if <hi>I</hi> have found no better effects of all this; how alas! have ſome of thoſe been neglected and oppreſſed, who had ſcarce one of thoſe advantages? Verily <hi>I</hi> am perſwaded, that <hi>God</hi> purpoſely corrected me for my ſins, by keeping me ſo many years under <hi>Oppreſſions,</hi> occaſioning my continual attendance in places of <hi>publick Tranſactions,</hi> that <hi>I</hi> might be an <hi>Eye-witneſs</hi> of thoſe Prevarications which have occaſioned ſo many <hi>Changes</hi> within ſo ſhort a time, &amp; that I might leave a memorial of it to thoſe whom it may concern hereafter: for, ſuch things <hi>I</hi> ſhould never have believed, in a time wherein ſo much honeſty and Religion is profeſſed, if <hi>I</hi> my ſelf had not heard them, ſeen them, and felt ſomewhat of them in my own perſon, to aſcertain me, that they proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not from thoſe Cauſes, which are by ſome pretended, to extenuate or excuſe them.</p>
               <p>It is not altogether <hi>publick want,</hi> as is alleaged, which hath kept me and many other diſtreſſed men, from their debts due upon the <hi>Publick Faith;</hi> or cauſed that the <hi>Parliaments Engagements</hi> have
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116002:7"/>not been performed; or, that their <hi>Securities</hi> are made ſnares, and ineffectual: But, <hi>Malice, Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Selfneſs, Vanity,</hi> or <hi>Negligence</hi> at beſt, have been the chief occaſions thereof, as I could demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate by many particulars, which <hi>I</hi> forbear, leſt it may reflect upon thoſe whoſe honour <hi>I</hi> deſire to preſerve, and upon ſome <hi>individual perſons,</hi> whom <hi>I</hi> hope to be now ſorry for their failings. <hi>I</hi> could make it evident, that ſince <hi>I</hi> complained of <hi>Oppreſſion,</hi> by the detaining what is my due, many <hi>vaſt ſums</hi> have been vainly and needleſly (<hi>I</hi> will not ſay wickedly) ſquandred away, which might have been beſtowed more for the <hi>Commonwealths</hi> honour and profit, in diſengaging the <hi>Nation,</hi> from juſt debts long due to poor <hi>diſtreſſed Men, Women</hi> and <hi>Orphans;</hi> ſuch as <hi>I</hi> have ſeen attending early and late, and from day to day ſolliciting for relief of their urgent neceſſities, with Tears, Exclamations and Imprecations, without any regard vouchſafed to their importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties or diſtreſſed Conditions; except ſuch a diſſembled regard, as increaſed their neceſſities, by giving falſe hopes of that performance, which they never made, neither perhaps ever intended. Who obſerved not how much was lately conſumed in <hi>Flaſhy Bawbles,</hi> whilſt thoſe poor <hi>Suppliants</hi> periſhed by want of neceſſaries? And how much alſo hath been loſt, by defrauding the <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,</hi> and neglecting that means of ſupply which was lawfully due? <hi>I</hi> profeſs in the fear of God, my belief is, by what <hi>I</hi> have heard, ſeen and obſerved, during the 17 years wherein <hi>I</hi> have been treading the <hi>Maze,</hi> and running round in the <hi>Wheel</hi> of my yet endleſs <hi>Sollicitations,</hi> that the <hi>Mulcts</hi> and <hi>Fines</hi> which might have juſtly been raiſed upon <hi>Diſcoveries</hi> (and which might have been made) out of their <hi>Eſtates,</hi> who have falſified their truſt, cheated, diſhonoured, or been miſchievous Enemies to the <hi>Government,</hi> and <hi>this Republick,</hi> (and the payment whereof hath been prevented by <hi>Bribes</hi> taken (or upon other conſiderations as unjuſtifiable) to the uſe of <hi>ſingle Perſons,</hi> or ſhared among <hi>parties</hi> in <hi>Power,</hi> intruſted by the <hi>Commonwealth</hi>) would have more then diſcharged all her Engagements, and afforded alſo a Remainder for publick uſes; eſpecially if the <hi>Poſtmaſterſhip,</hi> with ſuch other means of raiſing money, had been from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, husbanded for the publick advantage. Why ſhould any thing, to that end diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable, be otherwiſe diſpoſed of, at this time, then for the Publick, and to preſerve their <hi>Lives, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates</hi> and <hi>Credits,</hi> who ask but their own, and have hazarded and ſpent it in her ſervice? Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, whilſt the <hi>Common-faith</hi> is ingaged, ſhould any part of the <hi>Forreſts</hi> (with the tyrannous Laws to them pertaining) be reſerved to feed wild beaſts for the diſport of <hi>vain</hi> and <hi>idle perſons?</hi> and to give occaſion of reviving again hereafter that <hi>Oppreſſion,</hi> which was one of the greateſt under which this Land heretofore groaned? Or, why ſhould the Accompts of ſo many <hi>Sequeſtrators,</hi> and <hi>Receivers,</hi> lye unexamined, by whom much money was received, which is not yet ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted for, or paid into the <hi>Common-Treaſury,</hi> to ſupply publick wants? And wherefore, during the preſent <hi>neceſſities,</hi> ſhould it not be reputed as honourable an <hi>Expedient,</hi> to pay this <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths</hi> debts, by conferring to that end, all Offices thereby diſpoſable, (with a competent allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance for their execution) and by ſelling thoſe that are ſaleable, (and not for adminiſtration of <hi>Juſtice</hi>) as it is to give them in reward of <hi>ſervices done,</hi> or to beſtow a <hi>Plurality</hi> of places and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable Offices (ſometimes <hi>two, three, four,</hi> yea more at once) upon one perſon, who is neither neceſſitous, nor perhaps hath any way deſerved ſo much as one of them? All which Particulars, with many other unmentioned, when I have well thought upon, as oftentimes I do, I cannot chuſe but believe, that either this <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> is not ſo poor as it is pretended to be, or elſe that there are ſome very much to blame.</p>
               <p>But, I hope, thoſe <hi>failings</hi> which were heretofore, will be now amended, and things better ordered hereafter: For theſe <hi>miſactings and neglects,</hi> with ſome other, have exceedingly incenſed the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and were doubtleſs an occaſion in part, of that dangerous <hi>Inſurrection</hi> which is newly begun in ſeveral places, and like to be univerſal, if GOD prevent it not by mercifully quenching thoſe <hi>Flames</hi> without pouring upon them much blood; as I believ he will, for the ſafety of his <hi>choſen ones</hi> among us, and to deceive the hopes, and fruſtrate the purpoſes of his and our <hi>malitious Enemies,</hi> who at this time, (by what is deſigned here &amp; in forraign parts) do preſume, they ſhall get a large ſtep toward the advance of their own <hi>Kingdome,</hi> by our deſtruction: and ſo it will be, if he put not a Bridle in their mouths: Therefore, when that day of ſalvation appeareth, it will become us to be <hi>thankful</hi> in <hi>humility,</hi> to <hi>rejoyce</hi> with <hi>trembling,</hi> and to uſe that victory, which God ſhall be pleaſed to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:116002:7"/>give, over our <hi>ſeduced Brethren</hi> and <hi>Country-men,</hi> with moderation, as men conſcious in our ſelves, that they are thereby corrected as well for <hi>our ſins,</hi> as for <hi>their own;</hi> as alſo, with that fellow-feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which our <hi>natural body</hi> would have, if ſome <hi>members</hi> thereof were tormented, or to be cut off: for, conſidering that their <hi>provocations,</hi> or <hi>miſunderſtandings,</hi> (as it is probable,) tranſported a great part of them with a blinde and prepoſterous zeal to their <hi>Country,</hi> rather then any malice the eunto; and, conſidering that many of them are not only ſeduced by the ſubtile Arguments and inſinuations of <hi>ſeeming friends,</hi> who intended one thing whilſt they pretended another, but alſo really believed in their own hearts they had a <hi>good cauſe,</hi> (and that the <hi>miſcarriages</hi> which they ſaw, and the <hi>miſconſtitutions</hi> from which they conceived them to ſpring, did oblige them to vindicate their own and the whole <hi>Nations</hi> rights and freedoms, from that intrenchment, which in their judgement ſeemed to be made upon them) they may be objects of <hi>Pity</hi> in ſome meaſure. God incline them whom it concerns, to be <hi>juſt</hi> as he is <hi>juſt,</hi> and <hi>merciful</hi> as he is <hi>merciful,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that proportion whereof man is capable. I will now again proceed with what I have more to ſay concerning my <hi>particular Cauſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Parliament,</hi> is (I confeſs) much more ſtreightned at this preſent then formerly, as well in time, as in the want of many other things needful, by reaſon of that condition, whereto their Obſtructers and Interrupters have brought this <hi>Republick:</hi> in which reſpect, I have hitherto for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born to be over-importunate for my relief, and would have waited until it had been at better leaſure, and better able to redreſs my <hi>Grievances;</hi> but, I can now ſubſiſt no longer: and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently perceive alſo, that I muſt break in upon it, if I will be heard before it be too late. For, <hi>procraſtinations</hi> ſo multiply <hi>oppreſſions,</hi> inſtead of giving opportunities to diminiſh them; that, this <hi>Parliament</hi> (as it hath heretofore thereto happened, and to many other) may ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and unexpectedly be ended, before I ſhall be heard; and that their <hi>Leaſure</hi> and <hi>Treaſure</hi> never will be more, nor their troubles fewer then they are, unleſs there be a more impartial di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution of <hi>Burthens,</hi> and a more charitable regard to thoſe private mens <hi>Oppreſſions,</hi> who have been always faithful to the <hi>Publick Intereſt,</hi> and are now conſumed by their free contributions, and by the want of that which hath been kept, and exacted from them againſt their wills. If they believe GOD, to be juſt, and not like ſome among themſelves, how can they expect a bleſſing upon their conſultations and endeavours, whilſt they permit them to periſh, by with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding their means of <hi>Livelihood,</hi> who voluntarily engaged both <hi>life</hi> and livelihood for their preſervation? and whilſt they ſuffer thoſe who firſt ſerved them in their greateſt need, to be quite <hi>forgotten</hi> (as to things which may concern their weal and ſafety) or to be laſt <hi>remembred,</hi> except it be by thoſe only, who watch for opportunities to deſtroy or diſgrace them?</p>
               <p>Such there be, even among thoſe, who ſhould be more mindful of Gods <hi>justice</hi> upon <hi>themſelves,</hi> and of his late <hi>ſuperlative mercy</hi> to them and us, in reſtoring their <hi>loſt Power,</hi> and in vouchſafing to make them his <hi>Probationers</hi> once more. Theſe, I would not fear to diſtinguiſh from others by <hi>Name,</hi> if I had <hi>warrant</hi> for it, and, as good proofs to aſcertain their miſchievous and malicious condition to other men, as I have to aſſure my ſelf of it. Such we have diſcovered to have been among them heretofore; and ſuch to be there now, <hi>they themſelves</hi> will diſcover ere long: and perhaps, I could offer to the conſideration of ſuch as theſe, that, concerning their own <hi>perſons</hi> and <hi>families</hi> (which they think unknown to the world) that would make them afraid there is a GOD, though he be not yet in their <hi>Creed.</hi> Theſe, are the <hi>Achans</hi> which trouble our <hi>Iſrael:</hi> Among theſe, is that <hi>Jack on all ſides,</hi> that turns with every winde; that <hi>Politick would,</hi> befool'd with pride and over-weening, and that <hi>Love</hi> corrupted with diſſimulation and <hi>avarice,</hi> by whom many proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings relating both to <hi>publick</hi> and <hi>private Juſtice</hi> are obſtructed; and whoſe <hi>Tables</hi> are made a <hi>ſnare</hi> oft-times, to the falſifying of this old ſaying in barbarous <hi>Latine,</hi> uſual among ſome <hi>Lawers, Eſculenta, &amp; poculenta, non ſunt Bribamenta.</hi> Such as theſe, have added <hi>indignities</hi> to my <hi>oppreſſions,</hi> procuring me to be diſgracefully put out of that <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> wherein, I have faithfully ſerved my <hi>Country</hi> many years, to preſerve the peace thereof, according to my underſtanding, and as oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity was offered; and, they have ſeemed to rank me among <hi>Malignants,</hi> and perſons diſaffected to the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> by cauſing me to be left out of the <hi>Militia,</hi> in <hi>Hampſhire,</hi> where my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily is ſetled, and where it as much concern'd me to be Active, in preſerving my own <hi>intereſt</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:116002:8"/>and ſafety, together with the <hi>Common-peace,</hi> as any <hi>Gentleman</hi> in that <hi>Country;</hi> and (I may ſpeak it without arrogance) I have as well deſerved to be therewith truſted; and made my truſtineſs ſo well known, both to the <hi>friends</hi> and <hi>enemies</hi> of this <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> that I am ſure, the laſt, will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member it when it may do me a miſchief, though the firſt, ſhall forget it, when it may do me good.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Affront,</hi> had it concerned my perſonal <hi>ſafety</hi> and <hi>Reputation</hi> only, (though that is not to be neglected) I would have diſdained to take notice of it at this time, had I not cauſe to be jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, it tends further then to my perſonal diſadvantage; and, that I was not omitted by <hi>forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> or <hi>miſtake,</hi> but by <hi>deſign.</hi> They could not juſtly put me out of the <hi>Commiſſion of peace,</hi> who till then ſerved in three <hi>Counties,</hi> as a <hi>Commiſſioner,</hi> in regard I was never charged with any <hi>Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quency:</hi> Nor becauſe I had not a <hi>viſible eſtate</hi> there befitting ſuch a <hi>Commiſſioner;</hi> for, they ſaw an appearance of it; and if there be any Juſtice in this <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> it will be hereafter as compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent a <hi>ſubſiſtence</hi> for me, as I deſire, or, as may make me capable of that <hi>dignity:</hi> Nor was it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I am <hi>a non-reſident</hi> in that <hi>County;</hi> for, my <hi>Family</hi> hath been ſetled there above two years, and I have there acted by that <hi>Commiſſion</hi> when I was in the Country, which was five or ſix times in the year: and, if I had not been reſident, <hi>non-reſidence</hi> is not a juſt cauſe to leave any Gentleman out of the Commiſſion, who was inſerted, and hath a habitation in the <hi>County;</hi> for, then, moſt perſons named in the Front of the <hi>Commiſſion</hi> ſhould be left out, to the diſſervice of the <hi>Commonwealth;</hi> which, is put to no more coſt, then of ſo much room in a piece of parchment as will contain their names; and if they come into the <hi>Shire</hi> but once in two or three years, an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion may happen whereby ſome neceſſary piece of ſervice may at that time be done, worth the coſt, which had elſe been omitted. And, that I was not omitted or exploded by any <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfulneſs</hi> or <hi>miſtake,</hi> it thus appears; There are four <hi>Gentlemen</hi> in that <hi>County</hi> with my ſelf, (beſides another lately in Commiſſion, and now left out alſo) who bear both my <hi>Chriſten</hi> and <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>names,</hi> two of which, never being ſo authorized before, are impowred ſince my <hi>Omiſſion;</hi> one of them in the <hi>Militia;</hi> the other, both in the <hi>Militia,</hi> and <hi>Commiſſion of peace,</hi> diſtinguiſhed, by their places of habitation: and doubtleſs, he who put out me whom he found upon the Roll, and who am the moſt antient <hi>Commiſſioner</hi> of my <hi>Surname,</hi> and put in him whom he there found not, and diſtinguiſhed him by the place of his abode; did intend, not only to manifeſt thereby that another was put into the <hi>Commiſſion</hi> in my ſtead, but alſo, that it might be the more certainly known, I am knowingly <hi>put out;</hi> which, a <hi>Perſon,</hi> being one of the beſt men who ſerves for that County, (and who gave in my name) being informed of, profeſſed he knew not why, or by whom, I was ſtrook out.</p>
               <p>I, do not inſiſt hereupon, with any deſire to be reſtored to what I was, or to be inveſted with any new <hi>Truſt;</hi> For, I deſire the contrary, though ſome of thoſe, who were inſtrumental, to have me left out of all authority (leſt I might perhaps, have hindred their late deſign) do maliciouſly &amp; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truly, report I ſeek to be reſtored. It ſeemeth ſome diſadvantage, to have contempt caſt upon me at this preſent; But, if they prevaile, who have now taken Arms againſt the Parliament, I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive (by what I diſcover already) that I and my Family, whether I am authorized or not, are in hazard to be deſtroyed with the firſt; and a <hi>Juſticeſhip,</hi> or the little ſhare which I ſhould have had in the <hi>Militia,</hi> would have more endangered then ſecured me: Therefore it beſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes me, who ſo well know the world as I do, to retire as much as I can from her <hi>intanglements,</hi> and thoſe <hi>employments</hi> wherein I am ſure to be a looſer. I take moſt pleaſure in thoſe things which no man can give me or take from me; and love not to be toſt in and out, like <hi>a dog in a blanket,</hi> as I and many better men have been heretofore, according as we were <hi>thought upon,</hi> or <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten;</hi> or as the <hi>Commonwealths friends,</hi> or our <hi>Maligners,</hi> prevailed in <hi>Parliaments, Councils,</hi> and <hi>Committees.</hi> Such uſage (if no proviſion be made againſt it) will make every ingenuous man (whoſe <hi>free-ſpirit</hi> diſdains to be made a <hi>Shuttlecock</hi> for every <hi>proud malicious ſool</hi> to play withal) ſhun thoſe <hi>Places</hi> out of which he may be caſt with diſhonour, how well ſoever he ſhall demean himſelf. I may be very well pleaſed that I am left out of all <hi>Publick imployments,</hi> as the <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths,</hi> and <hi>my affairs</hi> now ſtand: For I may juſtly ſay, as it was of old Prophecied by <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> it ſhould be ſaid at ſuch a time as this, and I do now ſay it: <hi>I will not be a Healer, make me not a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:116002:8"/>Ruler;</hi> for in my houſe there is nor <hi>bread nor clothing: for my Country is ruined, and my Country-men are deſtroyed, becauſe their words and actions are againſt the LORD,</hi> Iſai. 3. There are enough am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious to be authorized, who have means to ſupport the Charge and Envy that attends <hi>publick Employments;</hi> let the <hi>Ruines</hi> of theſe times be under their hands: I am not qualified, (nor the wiſeſt men among us) for ſuch undertakings, if this (as I belive it is) be ſuch a <hi>time</hi> as <hi>Eſay</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes in the ſame Chapter, the effect of whoſe words, I will here inſert, that you may judge whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be ſo or not.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Lord of Hoſts, doth take away the ſtay and ſtaff of bread and water; the mighty man, and the man of war; the judge and the prophet; the prudent and the ancient; the Captain of Fifty, and the honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable man; the Counſellour, the cunning Artificer, and the eloquent Orator; Children ſhall be their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Babes ſhall rule over them; the people ſhall be oppreſſed every one by another, and every one by his Neighbour; the Child ſhall behave himſelf proudly againſt the ancient, and the Babe againſt the honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; they grinde the faces of the poor, and the ſpoil of them is in their houſes,</hi> &amp;c. Were the Prophet now living, he could not have more lively deſcribed this <hi>Generation,</hi> then it was pattern'd out in his time, by <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and <hi>Judah,</hi> and recorded in his <hi>Propheſie;</hi> nor can we expect better events thereupon then befel them, if GOD be not extraordinarily merciful. But how can it be amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, whilſt <hi>malice pride,</hi> and <hi>avarice</hi> do mask <hi>ſelf-ends,</hi> under <hi>publick pretences,</hi> even when dangers viſibly encloſe us, and GOD is beginning to viſite us again with the <hi>Sword?</hi> or with what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort can I or any honeſt man, ſerve his Country, where they who ſhould <hi>aſſiſt</hi> him, will rather obſtruct his endeavours, and <hi>destroy</hi> him? verily, if I were in a capacity to ſerve my Country as I have been heretofore, I am doubtful whether to be put in or left out of <hi>publick employments,</hi> would be moſt or leaſt hazardous, conſidering I know not above <hi>one perſon</hi> in <hi>authority</hi> within many miles of the place wherein I muſt now live, with whom I can more <hi>ſafely aſſociate,</hi> or <hi>more comſortably converſe,</hi> then with an <hi>open Enemy,</hi> or a <hi>ſuspected Familiar;</hi> and may truly affirm, that none of thoſe whom I have provoked, by engaging againſt them and their <hi>Party</hi> in the <hi>Field,</hi> on the behalf of my <hi>Country,</hi> during the <hi>Civil War,</hi> have to me been half ſo inhumane and miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous, (though they are ſtill my enemies) as many are, who ſeem to befriend me, and that Cauſe whereto I adhere; yea, though to ſome of them I have done good <hi>Offices,</hi> and no diſſervice, in all my life.</p>
               <p>This, implyeth ſomewhat, which deſerveth heed: And if I have any portion of a <hi>diſcerning spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, I</hi> do foreſee, that if I be ſtill neglected, as I have been, I ſhall be but <hi>ſingly</hi> expoſed <hi>a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-hand,</hi> to that <hi>diſgrace,</hi> and outward <hi>ruine,</hi> which will be more <hi>univerſal</hi> within a ſhort time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and extend to another <hi>Overturning,</hi> unleſs there be a more hearty <hi>Returning</hi> to <hi>GOD,</hi> by exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting <hi>Juſtice,</hi> ſhewing <hi>Mercy,</hi> and <hi>Self-denial,</hi> then I yet diſcover. By ſuch a Change, I may be repaired, and eat the Fruits of my former labours in peace, during the reſt of my life; elſe, I muſt ſpend my days in bewailing my afflicted <hi>Country,</hi> and my <hi>deareſt Relations.</hi> Many, in <hi>ſcoff,</hi> have called me <hi>Prophet;</hi> and (though I arrogate not that <hi>Title</hi>) I have been inſtead of a <hi>Prophet</hi> to this <hi>Generation;</hi> and have had ſome part of a <hi>Prophets Reward;</hi> for, I have met with that contempt and diſhonour in my own <hi>Country,</hi> and among my own <hi>Kindred,</hi> which uſually befell Prophets heretofore. I have not merited to be called a <hi>Falſe Prophet,</hi> by that mark which the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> hath given us, whereby to know him: that is, by fore-telling things to come, and endeavouring upon the fulfilling of them, to withdraw men from the true <hi>GOD,</hi> or from the true way of his <hi>Worſhip:</hi> But, I have, thereby taken many times, occaſions rather to withdraw men from their ſins, and bring them neerer to <hi>GOD,</hi> by declaring what ſhall befal the <hi>Penitent</hi> and <hi>Impenitent,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to what is threatned or promiſed in his <hi>Everlaſting Word;</hi> and, doubtleſs, whether I be a <hi>Prophet</hi> or a <hi>Poet</hi> (which two words in the Greek, ſignifie the ſame thing) I have done the <hi>work</hi> of a Prophet among them, in ſome meaſure, and it will have effects upon them at laſt, for their <hi>Good</hi> or <hi>Evil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Influences,</hi> from the ſame <hi>Spirit</hi> which inſpired the moſt ancient <hi>Prophets;</hi> have been vouchſafed to ſome in all Ages, relating to mens <hi>temporal Weal</hi> or <hi>Woe,</hi> as <hi>GOD</hi> hath been pleaſed to prepare them by <hi>Fore-warnings,</hi> though there hath been ſince the time of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> no <hi>Propheſies</hi> decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring any other <hi>Gospel</hi> or <hi>Principles</hi> of <hi>ſaving Faith,</hi> but what they have preached or propheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:116002:9"/>and if any <hi>man</hi> on earth, or <hi>Angel</hi> from heaven ſhould declare any other, I would not receive it, neither could believe it: By ſuch a <hi>proportion of the Spirit,</hi> as is conferred on many of <hi>GOD</hi>'s people, I, being aſſiſted in contemplating his <hi>Word,</hi> wherein his <hi>Threatnings</hi> and <hi>Promiſes</hi> be recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, did fore-declare, both <hi>verbally</hi> and <hi>emblematically</hi> in my <hi>Britains Remembrancer,</hi> and the <hi>Title</hi>-Page thereof, long before they came to paſs, many Particulars which were fulfilled, <hi>in</hi> and <hi>by</hi> the <hi>Changes</hi> which have been lately in theſe <hi>Iſlands;</hi> and (though more derided then regarded) many of them were accompliſhed in their ſight who ſcoft at them, and in part upon the <hi>Perſons</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates</hi> of thoſe who perſecuted me for divulging them. The reſt of my <hi>Fore-warnings</hi> and <hi>Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Predictions,</hi> then and ſince divulged, (and not yet fulfilled) will hercafter be verified alſo, though ſtill derided and ſlighted. Therefore, I will as <hi>Jonah</hi> did, (but with more charitable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations then I conceive he had) retire to my <hi>Gourd,</hi> even to the remainder of my now <hi>blaſted E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate,</hi> which like the ſoon withering <hi>Gourd</hi> of <hi>Jonah, GOD</hi> cauſed to ſpring out of <hi>nothing,</hi> in the <hi>dark night of my affliction,</hi> to be a ſubſiſtence and <hi>ſhalter</hi> for me during his pleaſure; and I will patiently ſit under it, whilſt it continues, to obſerve what will be the Event of thoſe <hi>Conditional Threatnings</hi> and <hi>Promiſes</hi> concerning theſe <hi>Nations,</hi> which <hi>I</hi> have to them applyed, according to what was <hi>prophetically</hi> declared, and exemplified of old, to fore-warn and inſtruct all <hi>future Ages;</hi> which being the <hi>Contemplative Objects,</hi> from whence I deduced all my predictions, they were no deluſive <hi>Enthuſiaſms,</hi> or derivatives from <hi>Aſtrological Speculations,</hi> but onely from the <hi>Conſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llations</hi> and Aſpects, which thoſe bleſſed <hi>Luminaries,</hi> the STAR of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and the <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles</hi> have to, and with, each other. That, which theſe promiſe or threaten, is all whereunto I have reſpect in theſe my Calculations; and, my reſolution is, to praiſe <hi>GOD,</hi> whether his appearances be in <hi>Judgements</hi> or <hi>Mercies;</hi> whether, he ſo ſmites my <hi>Gourd,</hi> (as that of <hi>Jonah</hi>) until it totally withers, or ſhall improve it, into a more durable <hi>Plant,</hi> to be a Refuge and Refreſhment for me and mine; yea, whether he preſerves me in this time of <hi>Troubles</hi> until they ſhall end, or ſweeps me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way (as <hi>I</hi> confeſs <hi>I</hi> have deſerved) in the <hi>common Calamity, I</hi> will unfeignedly praiſe him.</p>
               <p>If we do as <hi>Nineveh</hi> did, the <hi>Mercy</hi> tacitely conditioned, and thereto vouchſafed, will be our lot; which, <hi>I</hi> pray, hope and wait for. And that <hi>I</hi> may ſit the more eaſily, in expectation thereof; as alſo that the ſame <hi>ſeaſonable Fruit</hi> evidencing their <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> who are now in <hi>Power,</hi> may produce comfortable effects to themſelves and others, as well as to me, <hi>I</hi> deſire you to whom this ſhall come, (if it may ſeem reaſonable, and be in you power) to mediate, for one <hi>Act of Grace</hi> to be vouchſafed on my behalf, which is but this onely; that <hi>I,</hi> who have ſerved my <hi>Country</hi> in my <hi>Generation,</hi> according to my <hi>Talent,</hi> almoſt 50 years, at my own coſt, may be henceforth exempted from <hi>Publick Officiatings</hi> and <hi>Taxes:</hi> Which <hi>Favour,</hi> conſidering how early <hi>I</hi> began to <hi>act</hi> and <hi>ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer;</hi> how diſadvantaged <hi>I</hi> have been, how diſabled <hi>I</hi> am by what is detained from me, to bear the Burthens impoſed, (and how little time <hi>I</hi> am likely to enjoy thoſe <hi>Priviledges</hi>) will not over-balance my former <hi>ſervices</hi> and Contributions, though the like <hi>Immunities</hi> were vouchſafed alſo, to one perſon of my <hi>Poſterity,</hi> whilſt it continued. Such <hi>Priviledges</hi> were granted in the moſt <hi>generous times,</hi> and it would be an honour to this <hi>Commonwealth</hi> to revive that practiſe for an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to faithful and honeſt endeavours; yea, and ſuch a <hi>mark of their respect</hi> confer'd on me in theſe corrupt times, would make it appear to thoſe who live now, and ſhall live hereafter, that there was always a faithful and well-affected Party in this Parliament, ſtrugling againſt the <hi>Corruptions</hi> and <hi>Oppreſſions</hi> whereby honeſt men ſuffered; and that they prevailed at laſt, to the exaltation of <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Mercy.</hi> Your mediation for this reſpect, together with a timely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcention to the humble <hi>Requeſts</hi> in the concluſion of my <hi>Narrative</hi> (at leaſt ſo far forth as may conſiſt with the <hi>Commonwealths</hi> preſent <hi>neceſſities</hi>) will oblige me, by a <hi>specialty</hi> more then ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary; and ſuch a reſpective laying me aſide, may not onely enable me to do my <hi>Country</hi> better ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices in <hi>a private condition,</hi> then perhaps, my <hi>old age</hi> can perform in <hi>Publick Nigotiations;</hi> but by that means likewiſe, the <hi>Malignity, Pride</hi> and <hi>Eavy,</hi> which now diſturbs my peace, would quite <hi>wear</hi> out, or at leaſt in ſome meaſure abate, when I intermeddle not with thoſe <hi>Employments,</hi> whereof other men are ambitious.</p>
               <p>To obſtruct the granting of ſuch reaſonable <hi>Requeſts,</hi> and to detract from the <hi>Commonwealth</hi>'s moſt faithful <hi>ſervants,</hi> and other honeſt men disfavoured by men of <hi>corrupt Principles,</hi> it hath
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:116002:9"/>been the practiſe of ſome heretofore (even in <hi>Parliaments</hi>) cauſleſly to aſperſe abſent perſons, who cannot eaſily come to take notice of their <hi>particular Detractors,</hi> or to vindicate themſelves. This, to me ſeemeth a great breach of the <hi>Truſt</hi> repoſed in <hi>Members of Parliament</hi> by their <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors,</hi> who impowered them not to execute their <hi>private malice,</hi> under <hi>publick pretences:</hi> and as it is no mean <hi>injury</hi> to ſcandalize a man innocent, before the <hi>Repreſentative</hi> of his whole <hi>Nation;</hi> ſo, it is no leſs then a <hi>capital offence</hi> againſt the <hi>Parliament</hi> (in my judgement) to indanger the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it guilty of receiving <hi>falſe Accuſations,</hi> or <hi>ſcandals;</hi> which, if it were a <hi>natural body,</hi> (as it is a <hi>Body Politick,</hi> that hath nothing to do in heaven) might indanger the admiſſion of it into GODS holy <hi>hill,</hi> according to the judgement of <hi>David,</hi> in his 15. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> I have here touched upon this, in hope it may be a means of preventing the like practiſes hereafter. If not, it were but juſt, that every <hi>Member of Parliament,</hi> who miſrepreſents any one abſent to his diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in that <hi>honourable Aſſembly,</hi> ſhould <hi>Ipſo facto,</hi> be incapable of <hi>acting,</hi> or <hi>Voting</hi> there for the future, unleſs he had firſt ſubmitted to an acknowledgement of his overſight, or made good his <hi>Accuſation,</hi> as one in a <hi>private capacity,</hi> if he whom he had ſcandalized were a <hi>private perſon.</hi> In this manner, I my ſelf have been abuſed (as I am informed) as well in relation to my getting of that <hi>Eſtate,</hi> which GOD, by his extraordinary providence conferred upon me during my <hi>Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles</hi> and <hi>Oppreſſions,</hi> heretofore, (by making my <hi>enemies</hi> more helpful towards it <hi>againſt their wills,</hi> then the <hi>willingneſs</hi> of all my beſt <hi>friends,</hi> or my own <hi>endeavours</hi>) as alſo in miſreporting touching my <hi>ſufferings,</hi> and <hi>actings,</hi> in other particulars. Therefore, (that <hi>culpable perſons</hi> may be known as they are, and <hi>honeſt men</hi> cleared from Cauſeleſs jealouſies and aſperſions, as much as is poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) I could wiſh (if the <hi>Parliament</hi> thought it needful) that a ſtrict ſcrutiny might be made in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to every mans <hi>dubious actings,</hi> wherein the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> hath been conſiderably concerned ſince the <hi>Civil Wars</hi> firſt began; And likewiſe that an <hi>accompt</hi> may be given by every one who became extraordinarily rich while the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> was impoveriſhed; how, and by what means he hath ſo enlarged his <hi>eſtate.</hi> If what I have heard be true, I am a wonderment in that reſpect be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond many other; for I am told that a <hi>perſon of Quality,</hi> and a <hi>neighbour of mine,</hi> being in diſcourſe with other Gentlemen concerning thoſe who had increaſed their eſtates to admiration from a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry poor condition, was pleaſed to ſay thus; How— and —got their eſtates, I very well know, ſaid he, (naming two Parliament-men who had ſuddenly purchaſed very large poſſeſſions, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving very mean eſtates a little before) but how <hi>George Wither</hi> became rich, that, quoth he, I wonder at, and cannot imagine. To prevent therefore, ſuch wonderments, let an <hi>inquiry</hi> be made, beginning firſt as aforeſaid, with me, and be carried on by a <hi>Precedendo,</hi> until it hath gone round the <hi>Nation:</hi> and I defie malice and all the world to charge me with what it can.</p>
               <p>It may perhaps be further objected (becauſe, I have heard ſomewhat tending that way) to the rendring of your mediation for me to this <hi>Parliament,</hi> the leſs effectual, that during the time wherein <hi>Oliver Cromw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l,</hi> by GODS permiſſion uſurped their <hi>power,</hi> I was for a <hi>Single Perſon,</hi> and endeavoured to maintain his Reputation, in what I might; &amp; magnified the Title of <hi>Protector,</hi> as moſt honourable, and pertinent to our well-doing. It is true, that I did ſo; but my being of that <hi>judgment,</hi> as our conſtitution then was, merits no disfavor or neglect: For, I never was abſolutely, for, or <hi>againſt,</hi> a <hi>King,</hi> or a <hi>Commonwealth, with,</hi> or wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hout a <hi>Single Perſon,</hi> but according as GODS <hi>extraordinary diſpenſations,</hi> the preſent neceſſities, the Law of Common-juſtice, and the <hi>Peoples</hi> aſſent in <hi>Parliament</hi> made it expedient or not expedient; nor otherwiſe then the moſt prudent of this <hi>Parliament</hi> lately ſeemed to judge thereof. For, either way, a <hi>Government</hi> may be <hi>good</hi> or <hi>evil.</hi> The <hi>United Provinces,</hi> and ſome other <hi>Commonweals,</hi> have well enough ſubſiſted without a <hi>Single Perſon;</hi> yet the <hi>Venetians</hi> (the moſt flouriſhing <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> and of the lengeſt continuance of any ſince <hi>Chriſt,</hi> have their <hi>Duke</hi> without any viſible diſadvantage; and the moſt famous <hi>Commonwealth</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> had a <hi>Moſes,</hi> a <hi>Joſhua,</hi> and other Judges, who ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively exerciſed a ſingle <hi>Authority</hi> Let that be conſidered, as alſo, that it is my <hi>Principle</hi> to uphold the <hi>Power</hi> which by GODS <hi>grace,</hi> or <hi>permiſſion,</hi> is for the <hi>time being</hi> ſet over us; and that I may as much as in me lieth, preſerve the <hi>Common-peace,</hi> in a <hi>prudential way,</hi> until Gods <hi>Proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> are determined, and his <hi>ſecret will,</hi> is made manifeſt. Let it therewith be conſidered like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, that in all my <hi>Addreſſes</hi> to <hi>Oliver Cromwel,</hi> and in all things by me publickly or <hi>privately
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:116002:10"/>Written</hi> to him, or done for him, as the then <hi>Supreme-Officer,</hi> I had evermore a care, to offer un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his remembrance, and to other mens, that, the power permiſſively onely vouchſafed, was but <hi>Conditional:</hi> and, that if what was tacitely the <hi>condition</hi> thereof, were not by him perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, it would be at laſt the deſtruction of him, and of his <hi>Family,</hi> or of both, without repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: and that likewiſe, the preſervation of the <hi>Peoples</hi> juſt <hi>Freedoms,</hi> both <hi>ſpiritual</hi> and <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral</hi> (being part of that <hi>tacite condition</hi>) was by me inſiſted upon, ſo far forth, as it might be done, in thoſe times, and to a perſon in his <hi>place,</hi> without making all that to be ineffectual which I principally intended: as would more evidently appear, if all thoſe <hi>Caveats</hi> and <hi>forewarnings</hi> were publiſhed which I exhibited unto him, and others in private to that purpoſe, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding how diſadvantagious it would be to my <hi>perſonal intereſt,</hi> as my affairs then ſtood, and which were not a little hazarded, and made more deſtructive by the boldneſs which I then aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; who neither baſely flattered him, for my own ends, as many did, nor aſcribed any thing as due to him in the <hi>Place</hi> he poſſeſſed and exerciſed, but in order to the <hi>Publick welfare;</hi> and as he had been inſtrumental (at the <hi>Peoples coſt</hi>) in conquering thoſe for them, who had formerly deprived them of their <hi>liberties:</hi> For, I did only commend thoſe <hi>Actions</hi> of his, which were in themſelves commendable, without juſtifying him in his <hi>perſonal deſervings</hi> as to the intention, otherwiſe then their outward appearances might induce me to hope of it; and, whether or no, he was really ſuch as he pretended, could be certainly known to GOD, and to himſelf only.</p>
               <p>And, whereas, it may be yet further objected, that in ſome paſſages of thoſe <hi>Poems</hi> and <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes,</hi> which have been by me heretofore publiſhed or communicated in private, I have aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red or implied that the Power of this <hi>Parliament</hi> was <hi>neceſſarily interrupted,</hi> in reſpect of us, and juſtly alſo in reſpect of GOD, whoſe <hi>juſtice and mercy,</hi> have had thereby the more evident <hi>mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtations;</hi> I do confeſs ingenuouſly that I was, and ſtill am of that <hi>judgement;</hi> and do believe by the little ſorrow, and much rejoycing, which generally appeared in the people both <hi>well</hi> and <hi>ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected</hi> thereunto at the time of their <hi>Interruption,</hi> that moſt men were then of my opinion: For, it was not only, undeniably evident, that many proceedings were then carried on to the infring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Common-right,</hi> as well as to the multiplying of <hi>private Oppreſſions,</hi> by the prevalency of ſome <hi>corrupt Members,</hi> over-voting thoſe who were faithful to their <hi>Truſt;</hi> But, that a <hi>Malignant party</hi> among them, had alſo <hi>brought</hi> in, and were then continually <hi>bringing</hi> in, ſo many qualified like <hi>themſelves</hi> into their <hi>Houſe,</hi> and who were ſo induſtrious, either to break the <hi>Army</hi> by divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it, or, by raiſing up another againſt it, that it would probably have reſtored the <hi>Common Enemies</hi> to their <hi>ſubdued Power,</hi> or brought all to a deſtructive <hi>diſunion,</hi> and <hi>confuſion</hi> among our ſelves. Therefore, GOD, in <hi>justice</hi> to the <hi>one party,</hi> and in <hi>mercy</hi> to the other, made uſe of that which was perhaps corruptly deſigned, by ſome, for their <hi>own ends,</hi> and converted it, to bring his <hi>good purpoſes</hi> to paſs; particularly to prevent this <hi>Parliaments</hi> being everlaſtingly deſtroyed, by ſome of its own <hi>Members;</hi> To give them and others, an extraordinary <hi>experiment,</hi> by their <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bations,</hi> what they were in whom they confided; how little truſt there is in men exalted to honour, (how pious, how honeſt, or how mortified ſoever they are or pretend to be) and to humble thoſe who are now again reſtored, that, with thankfulneſs for his <hi>double mercy,</hi> in their <hi>correction</hi> and <hi>reſtauration,</hi> they may reforme in themſelves and others, hereafter, that which was amiſs hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. To thoſe ends, and for ſuch like, GOD, (as he did <hi>Nebuchadnezzer</hi>) drove them from the <hi>Throne,</hi> to live among the <hi>Common-herd</hi> until almoſt ſo many years as he was expelled; whereby, if they be not yet ſo humbled, as willingly to be remembred of it, to obſerve their former fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; to acknowledge with an <hi>awful rejoycing,</hi> theſe paſt <hi>tranſactions,</hi> and their preſent <hi>mercies</hi> and chaſtiſements, to GODS honour; &amp; to be merciful to others, as he hath been to them; and at ſeaſt to excuſe me for what I have formerly and now written, with a good Conſcience, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve my <hi>Countries</hi> peace, and their honour, without any purpoſe of diſhonouring them (as I hope they will underſtand it) then, not I <hi>alone,</hi> but all the <hi>well-affected</hi> of this <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> will be much deceived in their <hi>expectations:</hi> and we muſt ſuffer until GOD ſhall be pleaſed, to ſend us other <hi>Deliverers,</hi> or to deliver us himſelf: And, I do verily believe, that this <hi>Government</hi> as a <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> (or whatſoever it ſhall be,) will come to no happy, or proſperous <hi>Settlement,</hi> until it ſhall firſt do me juſtice, who have ſo long ſuffered, and been ſo conſtantly faithful thereunto;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:116002:10"/>and till they have embraced alſo, the Counſel of thoſe neglected <hi>poor men,</hi> who have contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and may contribute <hi>means</hi> for their preſervation, who had elſe been, and ſhall be deſtroyed. This <hi>belief</hi> or <hi>ſuggeſtion</hi> (call it what you will) I cannot expel though my life ſhould depend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, and though I have long ſtrugled againſt it; as proceeding from a <hi>ſelfiſh over-weening:</hi> and the ejection of it, is the more difficult, becauſe, when it firſt poſſeſſed me, it entred upon this <hi>occaſion,</hi> which I will faithfully relate. I was many years paſt, (as I think other men have been during the trials of their patience) more curiouſly I confeſs, then became a <hi>Chriſtian modeſty,</hi> deſirous to foreknow, <hi>what</hi> and <hi>when,</hi> would be the concluſion of thoſe troubles which GOD had brought upon theſe <hi>Nations;</hi> and, my inquiſitiveneſs, received this anſwer out of my own heart: <hi>Wouldst thou know the</hi> ſucceſſes <hi>before their coming, which GOD hath kept ſecret? Then, thus much, and by this</hi> means <hi>know it:</hi> Thou in thine own <hi>perſon, and outward condition, ſhalt be a</hi> ſign <hi>unto thy</hi> ſelf, <hi>what the event</hi> will be, and when: <hi>According as thou doſt externally proſper, ſo ſhall this</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment: <hi>when thou art relieved by their</hi> Juſtice <hi>from thy</hi> Oppreſſions, <hi>they ſhall be, within a while after, delivered from their Confuſions; and when thou perceiveſt, they have left thee to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, be aſſured, that their</hi> deſtruction, <hi>will not be long after.</hi> This may be only a <hi>melancholy fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie;</hi> but, a ſhort time, will diſcover, whether it be ſo, or not; and GODS <hi>will be done.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus, I ſometimes buſtle with the world, that, ſhe may know I am not yet dead, though I do otherwiſe, look <hi>ſheepiſhly</hi> (they ſay doggedly) upon my <hi>Oppreſſors,</hi> that, they may perceive I am ſenſible, how they uſe me; and though I am otherwhile a little ſurprized with a fit of <hi>melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> when I conſider what my <hi>Creditors</hi> and <hi>Relations</hi> do, or may ſuffer; yet, ſo little is my heart troubled in reſpect of my ſelf, that I would not change fortunes with any of them, when my condition is at the worſt, and their at the beſt; For, though they have broken my <hi>Estate,</hi> and crackt my <hi>Credit,</hi> if ever they break my heart (unleſs they break the Trunk, wherein it lies,) Ile forgive them. For,</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Haec mihi manent verba, perituro,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nec</hi> habeo, <hi>nec</hi> careo, <hi>nec</hi> curo:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Et, Veriora forent, in futuro.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>When I was young, theſe <hi>Words</hi> my <hi>Motto</hi> were</l>
                     <l>I, neither <hi>have,</hi> nor do I <hi>want,</hi> or <hi>care:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And, <hi>Death,</hi> will make them truer then they are.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>Make uſe of theſe <hi>hints,</hi> as <hi>opportunities</hi> are offered, and as GOD, ſhall move your heart, who worketh out ſometimes, by as ridiculous attempts as this may ſeem, effects which could not be brought to paſs by a more likely means. <hi>Saul</hi> went forth to ſeek only his Fathers Aſſes, but found a <hi>Kingdom;</hi> and perhaps, I who at firſt, hereby intended no more then to be eaſed from my <hi>perſonal Oppreſſions,</hi> may find ſomewhat thereby at laſt effected, which will give motion to that which will cure all our <hi>Publick Grievances.</hi> GOD, I hope will incline this <hi>Generation,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it be too late, to do that which will be moſt for his <hi>glory</hi> and the <hi>Common-ſafety;</hi> which is an unfeigned execution of <hi>Juſtice</hi> and ſhewing of mercy, according to the <hi>mercies</hi> received; and, whereby only, that great breach, newly made, can be ſo ſtopped, that another <hi>Inundation of bloud,</hi> break not in upon us. That acceptable <hi>Sacrifice of righteouſneſs,</hi> will drive away thoſe <hi>Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> which yet hang over our heads, and procure ſuch a <hi>bleſſing</hi> upon the <hi>Parliament,</hi> that it ſhall be enabled to ſetle a <hi>Government,</hi> which may preſerve both our <hi>ſpiritual and temporal Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms,</hi> inviolated, and from intrenching upon each other. A <hi>little Frankinſence</hi> ſincerely offred, appeaſeth <hi>much wrath;</hi> and perhaps, <hi>one hour,</hi> timely ſpent, to hear the Cauſe of a <hi>private Sufferer,</hi> ready to be deſtroyed, may be ſo acceptable, that it ſhall produce more toward a <hi>ſettlement</hi> in one <hi>week,</hi> then was effected in <hi>two months</hi> before; and their <hi>Oyl</hi> and <hi>Meal,</hi> ſhall be rather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed then diminiſhed, by making him a <hi>little Cake,</hi> out of that little which is left, if their <hi>faith</hi> be not more conſumed, then the <hi>proviſions</hi> in the <hi>Cruze</hi> and <hi>Barrel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If there be any <hi>Expreſſions</hi> in this <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> or in any of my Papers relating to the <hi>Grievances,</hi> whereof I complain, which may ſeem over-ſharp; be pleaſed to conſider <hi>how much I have ſuffred,</hi> and <hi>how long ſolicited,</hi> without effecting any thing but an increaſe of my <hi>Grievances;</hi> and let that plead my excuſe: If any ſhall be offended, that I declare thoſe <hi>Truths</hi> (which many are not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to hear of) in ſuch <hi>Language,</hi> and in ſuch a <hi>mode,</hi> as is not uſual with <hi>oppreſſed Suppliants;</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:116002:11"/>Let it be conſidered, that this is a time, wherein the deaf, dumb and blinde <hi>Devils</hi> which poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſs men, are not to be caſt out by ordinary <hi>Charms:</hi> and that, I am yet left in a worſe conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then many of the <hi>Commonwealths</hi> moſt malicious enemies, <hi>their guiltineſs excepted:</hi> For, my <hi>life</hi> and <hi>eſtate</hi> being innocently taken away, would have been a <hi>mercy,</hi> compared to that <hi>ſhame</hi> and <hi>vexation of ſpirit,</hi> which my <hi>Oppreſſions</hi> have occaſioned at ſometimes, not only, by the ſcandalous upbraidings and importunities of my neceſſitous <hi>Creditors,</hi> and by the ſence which I have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten had of expoſing my <hi>deareſt Relations</hi> to unſufferable wants and griefs; or by the indangering and looſing my <hi>Credit,</hi> as well as my <hi>Eſtate;</hi> But, alſo, by ſome <hi>ſecret trials</hi> of my <hi>ſaith</hi> and <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,</hi> in concernments of a higher nature, whereof the world ſhall never know.</p>
               <p>Thus much, being expreſt, for the reaſons aforementioned, and to eaſe my heart, by ordering into <hi>words,</hi> ſome part of thoſe many <hi>confuſed thoughts,</hi> which lay troubleſomely indigeſted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me; it hath made my condition ſeem to be more tolerable, then I thought it of late; and it hath ſomewhat quieted my minde, becauſe, this will partly anſwer for me, to many objections made in places, where I ſhall not be preſent to hear them: it may alſo ſave or recover ſome part of my <hi>Credit,</hi> by declaring to thoſe whom it may concern, that my failing a while the Expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of my <hi>Creditors,</hi> proceeded not from any <hi>diſhoneſt principle,</hi> or purpoſed wrong, but from ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voydable <hi>neceſſities;</hi> and that it ariſeth not from any diſſatisfaction to the preſent <hi>Government,</hi> that I am not ſo ſerviceable thereto as I have been, and ſhould ſtill be, (notwithſtanding all former neglects) if I had been able.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> have ſomewhat more to adde, and feel a <hi>Rapture</hi> coming upon me, which will conſtrain me to declare, that which is more conſiderable then my <hi>private Grievances;</hi> But <hi>Proſe</hi> is not ſo proper to that ſubject, as <hi>Verſiſying;</hi> and therefore, I will walk to the concluſion of what remains, upon my <hi>Feet</hi> in <hi>Verſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <lg>
                  <l>THough very <hi>much,</hi> and <hi>long,</hi> I have endur'd,</l>
                  <l>And, <hi>desp'rate Griefs,</hi> muſt <hi>desp'ratly be cur'd;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I, try no <hi>extaordinary Courſes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Till ſtrong <hi>neceſſity</hi> thereto inforces:</l>
                  <l>For, though ſometimes, I feel ſo great a ſmart,</l>
                  <l>That, I am therewith pinched at the <hi>heart,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I, ſtill finde eaſe, within a little ſpace,</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Patience,</hi> well prepared with <hi>Herb-grace.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My <hi>Genius,</hi> lately mov'd me to this <hi>Charm,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Which, if it doth no <hi>good,</hi> can do no <hi>harm</hi>)</l>
                  <l>And, therefore, I thus prove it: GOD, <hi>direct</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And, bleſs it, with a prosperous effect:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For, if what <hi>over-hangs us,</hi> at this time,</l>
                  <l>Nor <hi>Prayers, Narrative,</hi> nor <hi>Proſe,</hi> nor <hi>Rime,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nor <hi>Reaſon,</hi> can incline this <hi>Generation</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In <hi>ſixteen years,</hi> to <hi>Juſtice,</hi> or <hi>Compaſſion,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I,</hi> ſhall believe my days of <hi>private mourning,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Muſt, till another <hi>Publick-overturning</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Prolonged be; or, elſe, till <hi>I</hi> ſhall have</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Cure</hi> for all my <hi>Suffrings,</hi> in the <hi>Grave.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>However, (as <hi>I</hi> do) <hi>I</hi> will till then</l>
                  <l>To keep my <hi>Claims</hi> on foot, employ my <hi>Pen</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Sometimes in private, to make Proof of thoſe</l>
                  <l>Who to the World-ward, have made <hi>holy ſhows</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That either by their ayd, <hi>I</hi> may obtain,</l>
                  <l>What, <hi>I</hi> have long petition'd for in vain;</l>
                  <l>Or, that to men unborn, I may declare</l>
                  <l>How <hi>mercileſs,</hi> their <hi>Predeceſſors,</hi> were;</l>
                  <l>How ſhameleſly unjuſt; how may <hi>ways</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>GOD proved them; how many ſeveral <hi>days,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Weeks, months</hi> and <hi>years,</hi> he waited, to make tryal,</l>
                  <l>How long, they would defer that <hi>ſelf-denial</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which they had voted; and that, <hi>times to come,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>May glorifie GOD, in the <hi>Final Doom;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which, to the <hi>World,</hi> will openly be known</l>
                  <l>In greater <hi>Judgments,</hi> or, in mercy ſhown,</l>
                  <l>When our <hi>three Factions,</hi> parallel to them,</l>
                  <l>Which were the <hi>Ruine,</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Have acted out, their <hi>Parts;</hi> and left the <hi>Stage,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To thoſe, who ſhall begin another <hi>Age.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>GOD, is the ſame, in all his <hi>Attributes</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Whatere to him, our Vanity imputes)</l>
                  <l>And, juſt now, by the Eies of <hi>Contemplation,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> ſee a <hi>mixed-Cup</hi> in preparation,</l>
                  <l>Wherein, ſuch <hi>Drugs</hi> are blended, <hi>ſharp</hi> &amp; <hi>ſweet,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As, for our preſent <hi>Maladies</hi> are meet;</l>
                  <l>By which, <hi>I</hi> geſs, what things may come to paſs,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Good,</hi> or <hi>Evil Counſels</hi> we embrace;</l>
                  <l>And, <hi>I</hi> will tell my <hi>Thoughts,</hi> though being told,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> fear, they will be ſlighted as of old:</l>
                  <l>For, <hi>I</hi> confeſs, that which my <hi>Soul</hi> foreſees,</l>
                  <l>She ſees like him, who ſaw, <hi>men walk like trees.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The ruine of that BEAST, is now at hand,</l>
                  <l>Which doth as yet, the <hi>HOLY-LAMB</hi> withſtand;</l>
                  <l>And, he of late, hath ſo affrighted been,</l>
                  <l>Leſt, his approaching <hi>Downfal</hi> muſt begin</l>
                  <l>Among theſe <hi>Nations,</hi> that, with all his might.</l>
                  <l>He ſeeketh means his <hi>Vaſſals</hi> to unite</l>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:116002:11"/>
                  <l>Who muſt aſſiſt him; and in ſecret wiſe,</l>
                  <l>He hath conveyed hither, in <hi>diſguize,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thoſe <hi>Locuſts,</hi> which aſcended with a <hi>ſmoke,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whereby, they unperceiv'd, <hi>Diſguizes</hi> took</l>
                  <l>Of ſev'ral <hi>Forms,</hi> reſembling many <hi>Creatures</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of diff'ring <hi>Shapes,</hi> and of as diffring <hi>Natures,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To hide their <hi>Fraud; Theſe,</hi> lately pow'r have had</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Sorceries,</hi> to make the people mad,</l>
                  <l>And, by fomenting <hi>Diſcords,</hi> to deſtroy</l>
                  <l>The means, whereby, that <hi>peace</hi> they might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy</l>
                  <l>Which would preſerve them, &amp; prepare a <hi>path</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To that great <hi>work,</hi> which <hi>God</hi> determin'd hath.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For, though the <hi>ſons of Belial,</hi> do condemn</l>
                  <l>This <hi>Power,</hi> which <hi>God</hi> hath now ſet over them,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe, in <hi>outward ſhew,</hi> no ſuch effect</l>
                  <l>Is like to ſpring, from thence, as they expect;</l>
                  <l>Yet, ſhall the <hi>Power</hi> (againſt which many <hi>prate,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>raile,</hi> and <hi>write,</hi> maliciouſly of late)</l>
                  <l>Henceforth, from Violence, protected ſtand;</l>
                  <l>And be deſtroyed by no mortal hand</l>
                  <l>Except their <hi>own;</hi> and, till they ſhall in heart</l>
                  <l>From juſt and pious <hi>Principles</hi> depart:</l>
                  <l>But, either quite deſtory, or foil all thoſe,</l>
                  <l>Who, them, in their <hi>Authority</hi> oppoſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yea, though, thoſe <hi>Interruptions</hi> they have had,</l>
                  <l>Whereby, they are not, <hi>now,</hi> ſo able made</l>
                  <l>As they <hi>may be,</hi> when <hi>time,</hi> adds thereunto</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Compleatneſs,</hi> for the <hi>work</hi> they have to do:</l>
                  <l>They are, all that's <hi>remaining at this ſeaſon,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Conducible thereto, in <hi>humane Reaſon;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, what to diſadvantage them, doth ſeem,</l>
                  <l>May give them, at the laſt, the more eſteem.</l>
                  <l>The more contemptible, they now are thought,</l>
                  <l>The more diſhonour will on them be brought</l>
                  <l>Whom they ſubdue. If, they be <hi>poor,</hi> and <hi>weak,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The louder, to his <hi>glory,</hi> will that ſpeak</l>
                  <l>Which, he, by them effects, who foils <hi>proud Kings</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>mighty Foes,</hi> by deſpicable things.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This, is the <hi>power,</hi> whereto we ſhould adhere;</l>
                  <l>And, though to many men, it doth appear</l>
                  <l>Both by deficiency of <hi>Members</hi> lame,</l>
                  <l>(And, ſome, ſtill to retain, who do it ſhame)</l>
                  <l>'Tis <hi>GOD's Reſerve,</hi> to ſave us from <hi>the Curſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which we <hi>deſerve:</hi> and we ſhould make a <hi>worſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(As we are qualifide) if, he, now ſhould</l>
                  <l>Permit things to be done, as many would,</l>
                  <l>Who know not, what ſome underhand intend,</l>
                  <l>That make <hi>fair ſhews,</hi> their <hi>Freedoms</hi> to befriend.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>GOD, hath like <hi>Daniel</hi> in the Lyons Den</l>
                  <l>Them, from the beaſtly rage, of brutiſh men</l>
                  <l>Preſerved hitherto, (ee'n, when to me</l>
                  <l>It ſeem'd impoſſible, they ſafe could be)</l>
                  <l>And, this not for their <hi>righteouſneſs</hi> was done;</l>
                  <l>But, meerly for his <hi>mercy ſake</hi> alone,</l>
                  <l>That, thoſe <hi>few,</hi> who their <hi>truſt</hi> in him repoſe,</l>
                  <l>Be not inſulted over by their <hi>Foes.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For, in them now, the ſafety doth conſiſt</l>
                  <l>Of ev'ry juſtly-claimed <hi>intereſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, of each perſon, who ſeeks not to do</l>
                  <l>Thoſe things, that are deſtructive <hi>thereunto;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or, to <hi>himſelf,</hi> by breaking of that <hi>peace</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which tendeth to our <hi>gen'ral happineſs.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If to make up this <hi>Repreſentative</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>There do remain but <hi>forty men</hi> alive</l>
                  <l>Of all thoſe perſons, which all <hi>England</hi> thorow</l>
                  <l>Should repreſent each <hi>City, Shire</hi> and <hi>Burrough,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If they be perſons principled aright,</l>
                  <l>Who in the fear of GOD themſelves unite,</l>
                  <l>They ſhall perform the <hi>work</hi> that's to be done,</l>
                  <l>As if of their <hi>full number</hi> wanted none:</l>
                  <l>Nay, better, though among them there be ſome</l>
                  <l>Who to that <hi>work</hi> deſtructive would become.</l>
                  <l>That <hi>number,</hi> them, doth lawful conſtitute</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Cuſtome,</hi> and for Action doth repute</l>
                  <l>Sufficient (whilſt together they ſhall ſtay)</l>
                  <l>Though all the reſt abſent themſelves away,</l>
                  <l>And to exclude all, who offenſive are,</l>
                  <l>Though, one half of their <hi>hands</hi> and <hi>eyes</hi> they were.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>They are <hi>eſſentially,</hi> as fully <hi>free</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To all <hi>Intentions,</hi> as they need to be,</l>
                  <l>Or can be now made, without extirpation</l>
                  <l>Of that, which is for <hi>common preſervation,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Made lawful, by a <hi>Law</hi> confirming more</l>
                  <l>True, <hi>Soveraignty,</hi> then any heretofore;</l>
                  <l>Ev'n by a <hi>ſentence,</hi> for this <hi>Commonweal.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Decreed by him, from whom there's no <hi>appeal:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And all the <hi>Arguments</hi> which I have yet,</l>
                  <l>Heard or peruſed, to invalid it,</l>
                  <l>Are ſo infirm, ſo frivolous and vain,</l>
                  <l>That, whilſt it here, a <hi>Being</hi> ſhall retain;</l>
                  <l>I'll add thereto, my <hi>help,</hi> to make them ſtrong,</l>
                  <l>Whether to me, they ſhall do <hi>right</hi> or <hi>wrong.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which <hi>help,</hi> though chiefly it, conſiſts in <hi>words,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Will ſometimes be as uſeful as their <hi>ſwords,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Unleſs deſpis'd: And, if they can believe</l>
                  <l>What will be ſaid, ſuch <hi>help,</hi> this <hi>Charm</hi> will give,</l>
                  <l>Though it begins with <hi>terors.</hi> Mark it well:</l>
                  <l>For, 'tis a <hi>helpful</hi> and a <hi>lawful</hi> SPELL.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The <hi>Drums</hi> are beaten up. The <hi>Trumpet</hi> ſounds</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Alarums,</hi> threatning future <hi>Deaths</hi> or <hi>Wounds.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That <hi>Grand Conspiracy;</hi> which was foretold</l>
                  <l>And typifi'd, by <hi>Iſr'els foes,</hi> of old,</l>
                  <l>Is forming up a <hi>Body,</hi> to prevent</l>
                  <l>What may ariſe out of this <hi>Parliament;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:116002:12"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aſhur,</hi> and <hi>Ammon, Amaleck,</hi> and <hi>Tyre,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yea, <hi>Earth</hi> and <hi>Hell,</hi> againſt them, now conſpire.</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Foes,</hi> from all parts, do begin to cluſtre,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Gog, Magog,</hi> and the <hi>Man of Sin</hi> do muſtre</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Forces</hi> up. In their own <hi>boſome,</hi> lies</l>
                  <l>An <hi>Ambuſh</hi> too, of dangerous enemies;</l>
                  <l>And, nothing gives me ſo much cauſe of fear,</l>
                  <l>As, that, which may lye hid in ſecret, there.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet that <hi>fear,</hi> is ſurmounted far by <hi>Hope,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which, hath unto <hi>despairing</hi> ſet a ſtop:</l>
                  <l>For, they are that <hi>ſmall Remnant,</hi> whence may ſpring</l>
                  <l>Thoſe <hi>Armies,</hi> of our <hi>everlaſting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ing,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which will ſubdue the <hi>world,</hi> and ſet his <hi>Thron</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Upon the ruines of great <hi>Babylon,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>IF, they deſert not, what they have profeſt,</l>
                  <l>And, in his favour, loſe their intereſt:</l>
                  <l>That IF, remembring (leſt before the I,</l>
                  <l>We ſet the F, and cry aloud, Oh FI)</l>
                  <l>Let them be mindful, in <hi>humiliation,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That this <hi>year,</hi> is their laſt <hi>year</hi> of <hi>Probation;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And of all <hi>willful failings,</hi> now take heed,</l>
                  <l>Leſt worſe things, then befel them, do ſucceed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let them take courage alſo, and not fear</l>
                  <l>What, they ſhall either <hi>ſuffer, ſee,</hi> or <hi>hear:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For, he that ſaves by <hi>few;</hi> the <hi>wiſe,</hi> befools,</l>
                  <l>Defeats the <hi>ſtrong,</hi> and works with any <hi>tooles</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Reſideth yet among them; and will never</l>
                  <l>Forſake them, whilſt they do their beſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor.</l>
                  <l>That, ſo it may be done, let them ſtill minde,</l>
                  <l>Both what's <hi>before them,</hi> and what <hi>lies behinde.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Let them remember, <hi>He that ſtands may fall,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That, ev'ry <hi>promiſe</hi> is <hi>conditional;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, that, GOD's <hi>promiſes,</hi> will be to <hi>them</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Perform'd, as they to <hi>others,</hi> and to <hi>Him</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Perform their <hi>promiſes:</hi> for, though this wrong</l>
                  <l>He pardons oft-times, and forbeateth long,</l>
                  <l>There is a <hi>ſet time,</hi> which now draweth near,</l>
                  <l>In which, he will, no longer, ſo forbear.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let no man ſlight theſe <hi>Cautions,</hi> though by him,</l>
                  <l>Pronounced, who may deſpicable ſeem:</l>
                  <l>For, in theſe days, it often comes to paſs</l>
                  <l>That, GOD, ſpeaks, (as to <hi>Balaam</hi> by his <hi>Aſſe</hi>)</l>
                  <l>To <hi>wiſeſt men,</hi> by thoſe whom <hi>Fools</hi> they deem;</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Kings,</hi> by perſons that <hi>ignoble ſeem;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, if their <hi>Wills,</hi> as wilfully as he</l>
                  <l>They ſhall purſue, like his, their <hi>End</hi> ſhall be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This <hi>Power now ruling,</hi> raigns by God's <hi>Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yet, not without a <hi>fore-premis'd condition:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For, by <hi>unrighteouſneſs,</hi> it ſhall not ſtand,</l>
                  <l>Though it were as the <hi>Signet</hi> on his hand.</l>
                  <l>If, they themſelves with <hi>outward waſhings,</hi> flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</l>
                  <l>And ſhall not cleanſe the <hi>inſide of the platter;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If, thoſe defects of <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Compaſſion</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which lately brought <hi>Conſuſions</hi> on this <hi>Nation,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Be not forthwith repair'd in ſome-degree,</l>
                  <l>(As means by <hi>GOD</hi>'s grace, will vouchſafed be.)</l>
                  <l>And, if a <hi>Model</hi> truly Genuine,</l>
                  <l>This <hi>Auguſt ſixteen hundred fifty nine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Be not conceiv'd, and <hi>fully born,</hi> before</l>
                  <l>The time, exceeds the end of <hi>nine moneths</hi> more,</l>
                  <l>With all the <hi>eſſential parts,</hi> of ſuch a <hi>thing,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As may receive a timely perfecting,</l>
                  <l>(To qualifie that <hi>Rage,</hi> which may <hi>increaſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>Breaches</hi> made into the <hi>Common-peace</hi>)</l>
                  <l>Then, all that this <hi>Power,</hi> thenceforth can en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour,</l>
                  <l>Will either be a <hi>nullity</hi> for ever;</l>
                  <l>Or elſe, a <hi>furth'rance,</hi> to that horrid <hi>pother</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which will make facile entrance for another</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oppreſſing hand,</hi> that, will but <hi>Juſtice do</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So far, as <hi>Vengeance</hi> doth amount unto.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hear this with patience; altho ſpoke by me:</l>
                  <l>Conſider well, if thus it may not be,</l>
                  <l>All ye, whom it concerns: For <hi>Iſraels Rock,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Who hates requiting <hi>mercies</hi> with a <hi>mock</hi>)</l>
                  <l>Hath ſaid, that he muſt rule with <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who doth ov'r men, a <hi>ruling power</hi> poſſeſs;</l>
                  <l>And, we have felt, that <hi>Piety</hi> is vain,</l>
                  <l>Unleſs therewith <hi>morality,</hi> doth raign.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But, all may yet be well; unleſs, the <hi>Beaſt</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With <hi>many heads,</hi> mars their own <hi>intereſt</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By <hi>ignorance,</hi> or wilful <hi>diſobeying;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or elſe, our <hi>Truſtees</hi> (by our truſt betraying)</l>
                  <l>Fail in performing, at their <hi>promis'd day,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That, which is hop'd for, and for which we pray.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Moſt awful GOD' who when this world was made,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Gav'ſt that a</hi> Being, <hi>which no</hi> Being <hi>had:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Whoſe</hi> Wiſdom, <hi>from a Chaos made of nought,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>All things into a</hi> perfect order <hi>brought;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And, by thy</hi> Word, eternally Divine,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Didſt out of</hi> Darkneſs, <hi>cauſe the</hi> Light <hi>to ſhine;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Enable thoſe, who have the</hi> preſent Power,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To act, what will be for</hi> their Weal and our.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And now, Oh all ye</hi> people of <hi>this Land,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>At their need, aide them, with a liberal hand</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And loyal heart, to act for your avail:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Let not the fault be yours, if they ſhall fails</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lay all your</hi> Animoſities <hi>aſide,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For, though to them diſhonour may betide,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Conſequence thereof, will make you ſorry:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Their</hi> ſhame, <hi>will be the ruine of your glory.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If, otherwiſe it happen, what ſucceſs</l>
                  <l>May follow, 'twill be needleſs to expreſs,</l>
                  <l>And, to prevent it, <hi>I,</hi> thus often, here,</l>
                  <l>Adde this word <hi>IF,</hi> (which elſe leſs needful were)</l>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:116002:12"/>
                  <l>For, great will be our ſorrows, when they ſhall</l>
                  <l>Unmindful be of that <hi>conditional.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>We many ways lye open to perdition;</l>
                  <l>And, GOD, hath <hi>Magazeens</hi> of <hi>Ammunition</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Enough, to puniſh, all <hi>Offenders,</hi> either</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Singly;</hi> in <hi>parties;</hi> or elſe, <hi>all together</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As he ſhall pleaſe: yet, he vouchſafes a <hi>ſhow,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of ſuch things, as he probably may do;</l>
                  <l>That, we, our <hi>wills,</hi> and <hi>practiſes</hi> may bend</l>
                  <l>To act with <hi>Him,</hi> in what he doth intend.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thoſe <hi>Judgments,</hi> may not all at once enſue,</l>
                  <l>Which may be fear'd, and will be juſtly due;</l>
                  <l>For, <hi>GOD</hi>'s <hi>Long-ſuffering,</hi> ſhall perhaps once more</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Juſtice</hi> with <hi>Mercy</hi> mix, as heretofore;</l>
                  <l>And, prove us, by a <hi>means,</hi> that ſome abhor,</l>
                  <l>And, other ſome, have madly longed for.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>We have a <hi>Grand-Foe,</hi> whom he laid aſide,</l>
                  <l>And, will <hi>reſerve,</hi> till he hath foolifi'd</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Expectations,</hi> who forgetful grow</l>
                  <l>Of what they ſuffer'd, but a while ago:</l>
                  <l>And, as he ſhew'd how miſchievous a thing,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Jews</hi> deſired, when they crav'd a <hi>King,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By granting of it: (that, they might perceive</l>
                  <l>By <hi>feeling,</hi> what they would not elſe <hi>believe</hi>)</l>
                  <l>So, by the like <hi>Experiment,</hi> perchance,</l>
                  <l>He'll once more, cure this <hi>Nations</hi> ignorance:</l>
                  <l>Becauſe, the gracious <hi>ſentence</hi> by him given</l>
                  <l>On their behalfs, within the <hi>Court of Heaven,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Hath been by them deſpiſed, and contemn'd,</l>
                  <l>By ſiding with the party, there condemn'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Good <hi>GOD!</hi> how dare ſuch <hi>Traytors</hi> to pretend</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Countries Laws,</hi> and freedoms to befriend?</l>
                  <l>What <hi>Humane Law,</hi> or <hi>Power,</hi> will ſuch as they</l>
                  <l>With Conſcience, or due Loyalty obey,</l>
                  <l>Who diſobey Thine? Juſtifie thy Foes?</l>
                  <l>Thy awful <hi>ſentence,</hi> wilfully oppoſe?</l>
                  <l>And, either will have <hi>him,</hi> to fill the <hi>Throne,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhom Thou haſt thence ejected, or elſe none?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This <hi>Provocation,</hi> may thy <hi>Juſtice</hi> move</l>
                  <l>(By ſome enlargement of his <hi>Chain</hi>) to prove</l>
                  <l>How fit, for what he claims to be his own,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Out-cast,</hi> is by thy <hi>Corrections</hi> grown.</l>
                  <l>At that time, (if, it poſſible ſhall be</l>
                  <l>That ſuch a time, may be vouchſaf'd by thee)</l>
                  <l>If, he, unfeignedly himſelf reſigne</l>
                  <l>To that <hi>Courſe,</hi> which thy <hi>Providence Divine</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>May dictate, to compleat an <hi>Inſtrument</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For ſettling ſuch an <hi>equal Government</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As by thy Laws, and by the <hi>Laws of Nature,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Belong'd of old unto the <hi>humane-Creature,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, will conduce unto the <hi>Common-good,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVithout expence of <hi>Treaſure,</hi> or of Blood;</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Bleſſing</hi> might ſucceed unto theſe <hi>Nations,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Beyond our preſent hopes and expectations:</l>
                  <l>And, they, who now are plotting to make voyd</l>
                  <l>Thy <hi>purpoſes;</hi> would ſee their <hi>own</hi> deſtroy'd.</l>
                  <l>Then, ſhould the <hi>glorioust work</hi> be brought to paſs,</l>
                  <l>That ever for mans good, deſigned was;</l>
                  <l>And, <hi>way</hi> made, for that <hi>Kingdome,</hi> which their pride</l>
                  <l>Doth, as a meer <hi>Phanatick Dream</hi> deride;</l>
                  <l>And which, ſome <hi>Saints,</hi> too, (who in <hi>faith</hi> attend</l>
                  <l>The coming of it) much miſapprehend,</l>
                  <l>By fanc'ing things, which greatly inconſiſt</l>
                  <l>VVith ſuch a <hi>Kingdom,</hi> as is that of <hi>CHRIST.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhoſe <hi>final Conqueſts,</hi> not a <hi>Carnal-Sword</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Muſt make; but, that <hi>two-edged one,</hi> the <hi>Word;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Ev'n that <hi>victorious Inſtrument,</hi> the <hi>Truth,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhich doth proceed out of his <hi>ſacred-mouth.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, they, whom he doth arm againſt his <hi>Foes</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVith tother <hi>Sword,</hi> are but in place of thoſe</l>
                  <l>By whom the <hi>trees</hi> &amp; <hi>ſtones,</hi> were feld &amp; ſquar'd,</l>
                  <l>VVhen matter for the <hi>Temple</hi> was prepar'd:</l>
                  <l>Partly by <hi>ſervants</hi> of the King of <hi>Tyre,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Who wrought not for <hi>God</hi>'s <hi>honor,</hi> but for <hi>hire</hi>)</l>
                  <l>Partly by <hi>Solomons;</hi> who did intend</l>
                  <l>Their labours, to a far more noble end.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If, <hi>he premiſed,</hi> ſhall have an intent</l>
                  <l>This way to act; and ſuch a <hi>ſettlement</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Can bring to paſs, as may <hi>preparatory</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Unto the <hi>Kingdom of Gods Grace and Glory</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Appear to be; he, thereby ſhould attain</l>
                  <l>More <hi>honour,</hi> then to repoſſeſs again</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Kingdoms</hi> loſt, and to have thereunto</l>
                  <l>Annexed, three times thrice, as many moe:</l>
                  <l>For, then, that <hi>Roman-Monarchy,</hi> whoſe date</l>
                  <l>From her <hi>full-growth,</hi> with His, who ſprang from that</l>
                  <l>Seems numb'red, to the ſet time of their <hi>falls,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In that ſum, which her proper <hi>numerals</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Make up (when ſimply joyn'd in numeration</l>
                  <l>According to their worth in valuation,</l>
                  <l>Reck'ning from that year in which CHRIST was ſlain,</l>
                  <l>And in which, <hi>Rome</hi> did to her height attain)</l>
                  <l>Should fall by his ayde; and win him a ſhare</l>
                  <l>In that, which for thy <hi>Saints,</hi> thou doſt prepare;</l>
                  <l>And <hi>I</hi> do wiſh he may (by ſhunning that</l>
                  <l>VVhich hazards it, before it be too late)</l>
                  <l>Be partner in that <hi>honour,</hi> if it be</l>
                  <l>No bar, to what determin'd is by <hi>Thee.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He, might, then, poſſibly ſurvive to view</l>
                  <l>How far forth my <hi>Conjecture</hi> will prove true,</l>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:116002:13"/>
                  <l>Who (finding that the length of <hi>Satans chain,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And of the time in which that <hi>BEAST</hi> muſt raign,</l>
                  <l>Are, as they ſhould enſue ſucceſſively,</l>
                  <l>Summ'd, in M. D. C. L. X. V. and I,</l>
                  <l>Which takes in every <hi>Roman numeral</hi>)</l>
                  <l>Do geſs the <hi>time,</hi> when <hi>Babylon</hi> ſhall fall;</l>
                  <l>Will yet be forty years, or thereabout.</l>
                  <l>In which account, although I may be out,</l>
                  <l>Of this I'm certain; that it ſhall not ſtand</l>
                  <l>Beyond thy <hi>time,</hi> and that thy <hi>time</hi>'s at hand.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But, ſhould <hi>God</hi> (unto whom alone 'tis known,</l>
                  <l>What <hi>special mercy,</hi> ſhall to him be ſhown)</l>
                  <l>Vouchſafe to prove him, and he then contemn</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Courſe,</hi> which <hi>Juſtice</hi> will propoſe to him,</l>
                  <l>As probably he will, and covet that,</l>
                  <l>Which was by others, lately aimed at.</l>
                  <l>If, he ſtrive, to eſtabliſh ſuch a <hi>Throne</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As his <hi>forefathers</hi> lately ſat upon;</l>
                  <l>He, may prolong the <hi>Judgements,</hi> and the <hi>wrath</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which, on theſe Iſles, God's <hi>Angel</hi> poured hath</l>
                  <l>He, may be vexed, and inrag'd like them</l>
                  <l>Who, when they ſhould <hi>repent,</hi> do but <hi>blaſpheme;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As many now do, and as 'twas foretold</l>
                  <l>That (when GOD'S <hi>wrath,</hi> was poured out) they would.</l>
                  <l>He, may defer the <hi>mercies,</hi> which appear</l>
                  <l>To many of the <hi>Saints,</hi> approaching neer:</l>
                  <l>But, nothing better can be hoped from</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Kingdom,</hi> which his <hi>Party</hi> prays may come,</l>
                  <l>Or from <hi>himſelf;</hi> till we more cauſe have got</l>
                  <l>To truſt him, then his falſhood to the SCOT</l>
                  <l>May promiſe; or, their <hi>Tutorings,</hi> from whom</l>
                  <l>He, fraighted, with <hi>ill Principles</hi> may come.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Almighty God (ſhould he be pleas'd to prove him)</l>
                  <l>Can ſuddenly deſtroy him, or remove him</l>
                  <l>If he, when re-admitted, tyranniz'd,</l>
                  <l>Or, from what he profeſt, apoſtatiz'd:</l>
                  <l>He, that can make the worſt thing ſerve his ends,</l>
                  <l>As well as that, which to his pleaſure bends,</l>
                  <l>May make what <hi>proofs</hi> he will: But, we who know</l>
                  <l>No more, then what <hi>time,</hi> and <hi>events</hi> do ſhow,</l>
                  <l>Muſt Act as <hi>Reaſon</hi> dictates: Elſe, we ſhall</l>
                  <l>Or may be ruin'd, by what will befall.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If we well weigh what hazards they will make</l>
                  <l>Who, to keep tame that <hi>Lyon</hi> undertake,</l>
                  <l>W<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> from the <hi>dam</hi> hath liv'd wild in the <hi>wood,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And been a long time fed with <hi>human <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>bloud,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And alſo, what a <hi>charge,</hi> and what a <hi>pain</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It is to keep him always in a <hi>chain.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If, we heed well, what <hi>Plagues unſufferable,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It threatens, hither to admit the Rabble</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Malecontents,</hi> which that <hi>ejected King,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Would with him, by his re-admiſſion bring;</l>
                  <l>How much, thoſe will deceive their expectation,</l>
                  <l>Who are moſt zealous of his <hi>reſtauration;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, that, our <hi>charge,</hi> our <hi>dangers</hi> &amp; our <hi>trouble,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>They will in likelihood, much more then dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</l>
                  <l>Rather then make our <hi>miſeries</hi> the leſs,</l>
                  <l>Or, bring with them, a <hi>ſettlement of Peace;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Theſe &amp; ſuch things conſider'd, we, are more</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>mad-men,</hi> if we him again reſtore;</l>
                  <l>Unleſs, GOD ſends him for a <hi>puniſhment,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or makes him ſuch a <hi>real penitent</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As was <hi>Manaſſes;</hi> whereof, we yet have</l>
                  <l>No <hi>ſigns,</hi> nor ſo much faith as to believe</l>
                  <l>So great a <hi>Miracle,</hi> when there is nought</l>
                  <l>To us appearing, why it ſhould be wrought.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I, write not thus (and, GOD, ſo proſper me,</l>
                  <l>As this is truth) that, he debar'd ſhould be</l>
                  <l>From ought, which for his weal might be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd;</l>
                  <l>But, that, my <hi>Countries</hi> weal be not deſtroy'd.</l>
                  <l>I am no <hi>Foe</hi> to him, becauſe that ſo</l>
                  <l>He is to me; but, as my <hi>Countries foe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or, one, who ſeeks unjuſtly to become</l>
                  <l>Poſſeſt of that, which GOD debars him from;</l>
                  <l>And, I believe, (whatere he, may ſuppoſe,)</l>
                  <l>Scarce one man in a hundred, among thoſe</l>
                  <l>VVho, now his <hi>cauſe,</hi> or <hi>him,</hi> ſeems to befriend,</l>
                  <l>Doth it, for any conſcionable end,</l>
                  <l>Or love to him, ſo much, as out of hate</l>
                  <l>To thoſe, who now poſſeſs the <hi>Chair of State,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Through hate, or <hi>Envy;</hi> or, in hope that they</l>
                  <l>Shall by a change, be profited ſome way:</l>
                  <l>And that the moſt part, mov'd through <hi>levity</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Neither conſidring, what <hi>they do,</hi> or why</l>
                  <l>They ſo would have it, only, ebb and flow</l>
                  <l>According as the preſent winde doth blow:</l>
                  <l>For, moſt of theſe are but <hi>deluded Fools;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Men, from malignant <hi>Families,</hi> or <hi>Schools</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>New come; or, elſe, of <hi>deſperate Eſtates,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or, of <hi>crackt Credits,</hi> or of <hi>crackt brain'd-pates;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Or, ſuch as live by <hi>vanity</hi> and <hi>ſin</hi>)</l>
                  <l>Who, moſt deſirous are to bring him in.</l>
                  <l>And, I believe, that all men, whom he draws</l>
                  <l>To joyn with him, ſhall periſh in his <hi>Cauſe.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Tho ſome, (whom we know <hi>liers,</hi> and intend</l>
                  <l>To cheat us,) very much of late commend</l>
                  <l>His <hi>manners,</hi> praiſe his <hi>meekneſs,</hi> magnifie</l>
                  <l>His <hi>Chriſtian Patience,</hi> and his <hi>piety;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And have induc'd ſome <hi>hon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt men,</hi> to hope</l>
                  <l>He is not ſo vow'd <hi>vaſſal</hi> to the <hi>Pope</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As we have heard: yet, they who find the <hi>fraud,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And purpoſes, of thoſe who him applaud;</l>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:116002:13"/>
                  <l>(As alſo, whereunto they, are inclin'd,</l>
                  <l>Who <hi>publiſh this,</hi>) are not become ſo blind,</l>
                  <l>As not to ſee the <hi>bottom,</hi> and the <hi>end</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whereto their <hi>words</hi> and their <hi>endeavours</hi> tend.</l>
                  <l>And, theſe (not without cauſe) are much afraid</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Wolf,</hi> may in a <hi>Lamb-skin,</hi> be araid.</l>
                  <l>Theſe fear, that from the <hi>Skarlet Strumpets</hi> Cup</l>
                  <l>He, and his <hi>Party,</hi> have ſuch <hi>dregs</hi> drunk up,</l>
                  <l>That, they are now in thoſe <hi>Distemperatures,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which renders them incapable of cures;</l>
                  <l>And, ſo much, with thoſe <hi>vanities,</hi> beſotted</l>
                  <l>Whereon moſt <hi>Princes</hi> of the earth have doted,</l>
                  <l>That, <hi>theſe,</hi> when their hopes, are at height, will feel</l>
                  <l>(Like ill-wrought clay, upon a <hi>Potters</hi> wheel)</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Themſelves,</hi> to durt be crumbled in the <hi>making;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or, crack, and break to pieces, in the <hi>baking:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, that, whatere the <hi>Peoples</hi> dotages</l>
                  <l>May promiſe, there will be no hope in theſe</l>
                  <l>Or in their <hi>Prince;</hi> unleſs there may be given</l>
                  <l>A teſtimonial of their change from heaven:</l>
                  <l>Nor, will it be for our advantage, then,</l>
                  <l>Unleſs, we alſo, be reformed men.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>How, GOD, of <hi>him,</hi> or will of <hi>us</hi> diſpoſe</l>
                  <l>Is kept in ſecret, and he, only knows:</l>
                  <l>But, whether, he ſhall better be, or worſe,</l>
                  <l>(Likely to be a <hi>bleſſing,</hi> or a <hi>curſe</hi>)</l>
                  <l>He, neither is ſo <hi>good,</hi> nor yet ſo <hi>bad,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But, <hi>he,</hi> or <hi>ſuch another,</hi> will be had</l>
                  <l>As we demean or ſelves. Such, as are <hi>we,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Such, ev'ry way, our <hi>Governours</hi> will be.</l>
                  <l>For, GOD, gives ev'ry <hi>People,</hi> as their dues,</l>
                  <l>Such men to be their <hi>Princes</hi> as they chuſe;</l>
                  <l>And whether, <hi>good</hi> or <hi>bad,</hi> puts them together,</l>
                  <l>To be a <hi>curſe,</hi> or <hi>bleſſing</hi> to each other;</l>
                  <l>Till them from their <hi>allegiance</hi> he ſhall free,</l>
                  <l>As their <hi>demerits,</hi> or their <hi>merits</hi> be</l>
                  <l>Relating to themſelves, or unto him,</l>
                  <l>That is the <hi>Soveraign</hi> over both of them.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ah! were this <hi>Generation,</hi> but as <hi>wiſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As compleat, in their martial <hi>Bravaries;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or, but as <hi>meek,</hi> as they are <hi>wiſe in ſhow,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>knew</hi> as well, the things <hi>they do not know</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As thoſe they do; and could more lay aſide</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>avarice,</hi> their <hi>ſelfneſs,</hi> and their <hi>pride,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which bar them from the <hi>knowledge,</hi> &amp; the <hi>love</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of that, which would their beſt <hi>expedient</hi> prove:</l>
                  <l>They would begin, their failing more to mark;</l>
                  <l>Find how they grope, and ſtumble in the dark,</l>
                  <l>And, GOD, would give them <hi>open eyes</hi> to ſee</l>
                  <l>How, and whereby, their <hi>peace</hi> might ſetled be;</l>
                  <l>And that the <hi>Courſe</hi> whereby they thought to flouriſh</l>
                  <l>Is but a <hi>by-path,</hi> to their ways that periſh.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>As we are yet, our ſtruglings be in vain,</l>
                  <l>To caſt our <hi>burthens,</hi> and ſhake off, our <hi>chain:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>We do, but, when one ſide, doth ſcorch &amp; burn,</l>
                  <l>The other ſide, upon the <hi>Gridiron</hi> turn:</l>
                  <l>Or, ſhall but leap, (do whatſoe'er we can)</l>
                  <l>Into the <hi>Fire,</hi> out of the <hi>frying-pan;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Till, we our duties, better think upon</l>
                  <l>To GOD-ward, then we hitherto have done;</l>
                  <l>Until more generally, we do obey</l>
                  <l>This Power, which over us now beareth ſway;</l>
                  <l>Till alſo, they make good the expectation</l>
                  <l>Conceiv'd, ſince their <hi>additional-probation;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, till among theſe <hi>Nations,</hi> here be ſeen</l>
                  <l>A greater <hi>change,</hi> then hitherto hath been.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But, what <hi>change</hi> can here be, to ſet all right,</l>
                  <l>But ſuch a <hi>change,</hi> as muſt deſtroy us quite,</l>
                  <l>And make all new? unleſs, the <hi>change</hi> be made</l>
                  <l>By him, from whom, all things their <hi>being</hi> had?</l>
                  <l>Or, ſome <hi>expedient,</hi> or <hi>reſerve</hi> be found</l>
                  <l>Like that, made uſe of, when the <hi>World was drown'd?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For, moſt among us, are grown ſo deprav'd,</l>
                  <l>That, very few, can to <hi>Good uſe</hi> be ſav'd.</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>wiſdom, power</hi> and <hi>wealth,</hi> moſt men im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy</l>
                  <l>The <hi>welfare</hi> of each other to deſtroy.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Common-people,</hi> do not underſtand</l>
                  <l>Thoſe things, which GOD, and <hi>men</hi> have now in hand;</l>
                  <l>And, give aſſiſtance to <hi>rebellious Forces,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By <hi>railings, imprecations, skoffs</hi> and <hi>curſes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Inſtead of <hi>Prayers;</hi> and, ſo miſ-believe,</l>
                  <l>That, now, no Charmer, can them undeceive.</l>
                  <l>So harſh and general a <hi>Diapaze</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of <hi>diſcords,</hi> in no <hi>Climate</hi> ever was</l>
                  <l>Since in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> the <hi>triple-faction</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Foremention'd, wrought incurable <hi>diſtraction.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>No <hi>People</hi> ever were ſo blinde, ſo giddy,</l>
                  <l>So vain, ſo falſe, mad, fooliſh, and ſo heady,</l>
                  <l>But, where a ſad unparallel'd <hi>confuſion</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Threatned to bring a terrible <hi>Concluſion.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>They, like to <hi>Sampſons</hi> Foxes, from each other</l>
                  <l>Turn heads; but, are united ſo together</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Firebrands,</hi> by their tails, that, as well they</l>
                  <l>Who run the ſame, as they w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> thwart their <hi>way</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Deſtroy the <hi>Cornfields</hi> thorow which they run,</l>
                  <l>And, meet with greater-miſchiefs then they ſhun</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He, that oppreſſeth, doth of thoſe complain</l>
                  <l>Who, do apparent wrongs by him ſuſtain;</l>
                  <l>And, oft, finds means to tell ſo ſmooth a tale,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>innocence</hi> is daſht againſt the wall:</l>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:116002:14"/>
                  <l>He, that the <hi>truth,</hi> nor loves, nor tells, nor teaches,</l>
                  <l>Writes, fights, pretends, yea, pays, and prays, and preaches,</l>
                  <l>As if he did profeſs it without guile;</l>
                  <l>Yet, is a <hi>friend</hi> to <hi>falſhood,</hi> all the while.</l>
                  <l>Some, without <hi>honeſty,</hi> the <hi>truth</hi> profeſs,</l>
                  <l>Some, hold the <hi>truth,</hi> but in <hi>unrighteouſneſs;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, twixt theſe <hi>two,</hi> (as they the <hi>power</hi> divide)</l>
                  <l>CHRIST, and moſt <hi>honeſt men</hi> are crucifide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>With <hi>Tragedies,</hi> they make their <hi>Party</hi> glad,</l>
                  <l>And, joy in that, for which <hi>good men</hi> are ſad.</l>
                  <l>They love no <hi>news,</hi> like that which breedeth <hi>ſtrife,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lies,</hi> (as if they were nouriſhments of life)</l>
                  <l>They feaſt on; and at them, who their <hi>untruths</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Diſown, they ſtorm, as if then, from their mouths</l>
                  <l>The bread were ſnatcht: yea, when they know them falſe,</l>
                  <l>They love to tell, and hear, <hi>ſeditious</hi> tales,</l>
                  <l>By which the <hi>Common-peace</hi> may be ore thrown,</l>
                  <l>Although thereby, they quite deſtroy their own,</l>
                  <l>And multiply thoſe <hi>burthens,</hi> which, they lay</l>
                  <l>To their <hi>Charge,</hi> who, had took them elſe away;</l>
                  <l>Or, if not hindred in their <hi>enterprize,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By <hi>malice, falſhood,</hi> and <hi>Apoſtacies.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Their ſlandrous <hi>Tongues,</hi> and <hi>Pens,</hi> whom wound they not</l>
                  <l>Save him that is <hi>unknown,</hi> or elſe forgot.</l>
                  <l>They skoff, and jeer (not <hi>wickedneſs</hi> and <hi>folly,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>W<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> may be jeer'd) but things that are <hi>moſt holy:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, ſince <hi>times round began,</hi> no humane eyes</l>
                  <l>Did read ſo many curſed blaſphemies,</l>
                  <l>So much prophaneſs, and ſcurrility,</l>
                  <l>Or ſuch impure and filthy ribaldry,</l>
                  <l>As in this <hi>Iſle,</hi> hath in ſo little ſpace,</l>
                  <l>Been publiſh'd, to our <hi>National diſgrace.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But, what can more from thoſe expected be</l>
                  <l>Who think none but <hi>licentious men</hi> are <hi>free?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, whoſe ambition, more affects to have</l>
                  <l>The freedom of a <hi>Beaſt,</hi> or of a <hi>Slave,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then that which both by <hi>nature,</hi> and by <hi>grace,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Belongs of right, unto the <hi>humane race?</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Like <hi>earboar'd ſlaves,</hi> (who, <hi>bondmen</hi> have been made</l>
                  <l>So long, that, when their <hi>freedom</hi> may be had</l>
                  <l>They ſlight it) ſo do theſe; and, as conceiving</l>
                  <l>There were, no poſſibility of <hi>living</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In this <hi>world,</hi> (or hereafter to be ſav'd)</l>
                  <l>Except they ſerv'd a <hi>Tyrant,</hi> and were ſlav'd;</l>
                  <l>They, now rebelliouſly, a <hi>Captain</hi> chuſe</l>
                  <l>To lead them back to <hi>bondage,</hi> like the <hi>Jewes;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As if it were deſigned by theſe <hi>Nations</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To be like them, in all their <hi>deviations.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oaths,</hi> againſt <hi>Oaths,</hi> and <hi>Covenants</hi> are took,</l>
                  <l>Fitter to be repented of, and broke</l>
                  <l>Then to be kept; and, <hi>Piety,</hi> they make</l>
                  <l>A <hi>ſeeming warrant</hi> to infringe and break</l>
                  <l>That which obligeth all mens <hi>Conſciences,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, wherewith, nor GODS Laws, nor <hi>mans</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſes,</l>
                  <l>Thus, at this preſent, conſtituted is</l>
                  <l>This <hi>Nation;</hi> and, what <hi>change,</hi> muſt mend all this?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh madmen! (if ye are not ſo bereft</l>
                  <l>Of reaſon, that among you none is left)</l>
                  <l>Be you your ſelves the <hi>Judges,</hi> if I lay</l>
                  <l>That to your charge, which is not as I ſay.</l>
                  <l>Or, whether I dar'd ſay it, in a time</l>
                  <l>So wicked, without warranty from him,</l>
                  <l>Who, in this <hi>ſad day.</hi> of our <hi>Viſitation</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Inclines me to it, for your <hi>preſervation.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To cure theſe <hi>Frenzies</hi> for his <hi>future glory,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>GOD, is preparing a <hi>New-purgatory,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To purge what may be purged from the <hi>droſs,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That, of the <hi>Pure Gold</hi> there may be no loſs.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Judgements,</hi> now beginning, ſhall go <hi>round,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>through</hi> theſe <hi>Iſlands,</hi> till all thoſe are found</l>
                  <l>Who have been falſe, in that which they profeſt</l>
                  <l>To GOD, or to the <hi>Publick-Intereſt.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>From <hi>houſe</hi> to <hi>houſe,</hi> from <hi>man</hi> to <hi>man,</hi> they ſhall</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Proceſſion</hi> make, till they have ſeiz'd on all.</l>
                  <l>All ſhall be proved, whether poor they be</l>
                  <l>Or rich, or, of a high or low degree,</l>
                  <l>By <hi>outward,</hi> or by <hi>inward fiery trials,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Till they are brought to real <hi>ſelf-denials</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Twixt GOD and them, through <hi>mercy</hi> to repent</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>failings;</hi> or, to outward <hi>chaſtiſement.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thoſe, who ſhall in this <hi>Iſland,</hi> ſcape his hand,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vengeance,</hi> will ſeize on, in a <hi>Forraign-Land:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Foes of <hi>Peace</hi> among the <hi>Common-rout,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A <hi>Peſtilence,</hi> or <hi>Famine</hi> ſhall root out.</l>
                  <l>They, who have ſhuffled from the <hi>Souldiers fury,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shall fall into the <hi>mercy</hi> of a <hi>Jury;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, when they, from the <hi>Sword,</hi> are in ſome hope</l>
                  <l>To hide; ſhall then be hamper'd in a <hi>Rope.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>miſchiefs</hi> they have ſhunned in the ſtreet,</l>
                  <l>Within a <hi>ſecret Chamber,</hi> they ſhall meet.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe men, whom nothing <hi>publickly</hi> purſues,</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Conſciences,</hi> in <hi>private,</hi> ſhall accuſe;</l>
                  <l>They, who immovably do think to ſtand,</l>
                  <l>Shall fall, without the motion of a hand;</l>
                  <l>And when the things they <hi>fear'd,</hi> cannot annoy them</l>
                  <l>That, which they <hi>ſleight,</hi> and <hi>fear not,</hi> ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:116002:14"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Exceeding dreadful, during ſuch <hi>probations,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Will be the many <hi>ſuff'rings</hi> of theſe <hi>Nations,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Except thoſe days be ſhort'ned, or GOD, ſhall</l>
                  <l>Enable to ſuſtain what may be fall.</l>
                  <l>For, that, which now is coming to the <hi>Teſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is not, alone, the <hi>peoples interest,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As, what was lately controverted here</l>
                  <l>Betwixt <hi>them,</hi> and deceaſed <hi>Oliver;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or, <hi>him</hi> and <hi>Stewart:</hi> or, a thing ſo vain<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>As now, the <hi>Dane</hi> and <hi>Swede,</hi> or <hi>France</hi> &amp; <hi>Spain</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Are ſtriving for: But, whether <hi>good</hi> or <hi>evil;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>CHRIST, or the <hi>Man of Sin,</hi> GOD, or the <hi>Devil</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shall have the <hi>Soveraignty;</hi> and wo to thoſe</l>
                  <l>Who ſhall, that <hi>righteous intereſt</hi> oppoſe,</l>
                  <l>Which is to be decided, when the day</l>
                  <l>Shall come, to ſet their <hi>battels</hi> in aray.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But, <hi>'tis already come;</hi> at leaſt, ſo nigh</l>
                  <l>As to be ſeen by <hi>Contemplations eye.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tis come;</hi> and, (though not, as 'tis miſconceiv'd</l>
                  <l>By thoſe, who have a <hi>Throne</hi> for CHRIST con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triv'd,</l>
                  <l>As carnal as that is, which now muſt fall)</l>
                  <l>It will ere long, be viſible to all,</l>
                  <l>Who have that <hi>eye-ſalve,</hi> which may help their eyes,</l>
                  <l>To ſee <hi>Truth</hi> ſhining through <hi>dark myſteries.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>Banners,</hi> of both <hi>Parties</hi> are diſplay'd;</l>
                  <l>Both their <hi>Militia</hi>'s, are in part aray'd;</l>
                  <l>The <hi>ſouldiers wages,</hi> on both ſides is known,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>ſecret word,</hi> on many is beſtown:</l>
                  <l>And, not one <hi>Promiſe</hi> doth to me appear</l>
                  <l>Of an eſcape, from that, which men may fear,</l>
                  <l>Save, as in their <hi>Probations,</hi> they make good</l>
                  <l>Their charge, (though to the looſing of their blood</l>
                  <l>If need require) with truſting to that <hi>grace,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which, neither <hi>Is,</hi> nor <hi>ſhall be,</hi> nor ev'r <hi>was</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To any wanting, who did not refuſe it,</l>
                  <l>Nor when it is received, ſhall abuſe it.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But, what will follow, can alone be known</l>
                  <l>To <hi>them,</hi> on whom that <hi>grace</hi> ſhall be beſtown;</l>
                  <l>Or, by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Events,</hi> of thoſe <hi>Contingencies,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhich from a <hi>juſt progreſſion,</hi> will ariſe;</l>
                  <l>And, muſt, the <hi>ſteps-probationary</hi> be</l>
                  <l>To that, which is GOD's <hi>abſolute Decree;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For, whoſe accompliſhment, I will attend</l>
                  <l>Till that time comes, or, till my life ſhall end.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Here, I had ended; but it fares with me</l>
                  <l>As with him, who, again ſhall never ſee</l>
                  <l>Thoſe he departs from; and would leave be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him,</l>
                  <l>Somewhat, to make them, otherwhile to minde him.</l>
                  <l>Thus, would I do; or, rather, if I may</l>
                  <l>Make others minde <hi>themſelves;</hi> &amp; what this day</l>
                  <l>Seems drawing nigh. Oh, let him, with regard,</l>
                  <l>That ſpeaks for you, (not for himſelf) be heard.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let <hi>him,</hi> Oh <hi>Englands Repreſentative,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who, now, hath but a little time to live,</l>
                  <l>(And, fain would <hi>write,</hi> or <hi>ſay,</hi> before he dies,</l>
                  <l>That, for thy <hi>Weal,</hi> which thou ſhouldſt not deſpiſe)</l>
                  <l>Let him this once be heard, with that reſpect</l>
                  <l>Which may produce a <hi>rational effect,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Leſt, all thy <hi>Conſultations, Coſt</hi> and <hi>Pain,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Do prove at laſt, to be beſtow'd in vain.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To <hi>him,</hi> who to your <hi>ſelves,</hi> did you reſtore,</l>
                  <l>Your <hi>ſelves</hi> reſign, more now, then heretofore;</l>
                  <l>And, ſeek not, like your tyrannizing <hi>Kings,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>At this time, to contrive and ſettle things</l>
                  <l>More for your <hi>ſelves,</hi> then to advantage thoſe</l>
                  <l>Who, truſt in you, for better ends repoſe;</l>
                  <l>Or, to advance your <hi>Freedoms,</hi> more then their</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Juſt Rights,</hi> for whoſe ſake, they conferred are.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let not <hi>him,</hi> ſuffer more, who ſhall accuſe</l>
                  <l>For <hi>breach of truſt,</hi> then they who <hi>truſt abuſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As heretofore: For, there was once a time</l>
                  <l>Wherein, to charge a <hi>Member,</hi> for a crime,</l>
                  <l>Was proſecuted with a greater zeal</l>
                  <l>Then his <hi>Guilt,</hi> who, then wrong'd the <hi>Common-weal:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Ev'n when to <hi>Stangate,</hi> yea, (ſome ſay) well nigh</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Lambeth-houſe,</hi> the <hi>People</hi> heard them cry,</l>
                  <l>'Tis for a MEMBER: and preſerv'd was he</l>
                  <l>VVithin that <hi>Houſe,</hi> who ought expel'd to be:</l>
                  <l>And, all the <hi>mercy,</hi> to th' <hi>Accuſer</hi> ſhown,</l>
                  <l>VVas, to be kept a Pris'ner in his own.</l>
                  <l>But they who did it, were by <hi>Providence</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Caſt out; GOD keep all ſuch, for ever thence.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Conſider whether there do not, as yet</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To your own knowledge,</hi> men among you ſit</l>
                  <l>VVho much obſtruct the <hi>mercies,</hi> GOD intends,</l>
                  <l>And, your progreſſion in thoſe righteous ends</l>
                  <l>VVhich you propoſe. (I mean not any one</l>
                  <l>VVho erres through <hi>humane Frailty;</hi> For, then none</l>
                  <l>Should be excus'd) but ſuch as do tranſgreſs</l>
                  <l>Through Envy, and malitious wilfulneſs;</l>
                  <l>Or ſuch <hi>Preſumers,</hi> who, as <hi>Achan</hi> did,</l>
                  <l>Took <hi>Gold</hi> &amp; <hi>rayment</hi> (things, that were forbid,</l>
                  <l>On danger of a Curſe) ſuch as bereave</l>
                  <l>The <hi>poor</hi> of their ſubſiſtence; or deceive</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Commonwealth;</hi> and whom their <hi>Avarice</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To other things unlawful did intice,</l>
                  <l>VVhereby oppreſſed Innocents are wrong'd,</l>
                  <l>And Juſtice to their ruine, is prolong'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:116002:15"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Conſider, what may be the ſad event</l>
                  <l>VVhere any ſuch as theſe, are prevalent;</l>
                  <l>And, if you find ſuch, and deſire to thrive,</l>
                  <l>To them, in time, their due demerits give;</l>
                  <l>For, why, by palliating of their guilt,</l>
                  <l>Should your blood, like the <hi>Benjamites</hi> be ſpilt,</l>
                  <l>VVho brought on their whole <hi>Tribe,</hi> a wrath di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine,</l>
                  <l>For murth'ring but one <hi>Levites</hi> Concubine?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Conſider, when your <hi>Pardons</hi> were beſtown,</l>
                  <l>VVhether it were not for ends of your own;</l>
                  <l>More to ſecure your ſelves, or to befriend</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Nations Foes,</hi> who on your <hi>Grace</hi> depend;</l>
                  <l>Or, otherwhile, becauſe, you durſt not do</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Juſtice,</hi> which you were oblig'd unto,</l>
                  <l>Much rather, then ſincerely to expreſs</l>
                  <l>Your love to <hi>mercy,</hi> and to <hi>righteouſneſs.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If ſo, you finde, it; then, betimes lament</l>
                  <l>Your <hi>failings,</hi> and effectually <hi>repent.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Conſider, if, when we, to pacifie</l>
                  <l>The wrath of GOD, a day ſhall ſanctifie</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Faſtings,</hi> or <hi>Thankſgivings;</hi> whether, he</l>
                  <l>Can pleaſed with thoſe <hi>ſacrifices</hi> be,</l>
                  <l>Which coſt us, nothing, but to ſpend a day,</l>
                  <l>(And formally, to paſs ſome hours away)</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Emptineſs,</hi> or <hi>Fulneſs;</hi> or, to hear</l>
                  <l>Thoſe ſins reprov'd, which, we will not forbear;</l>
                  <l>Yet, not to leave behind us, till the morrow,</l>
                  <l>One ſymptome, of true <hi>thankfulneſs,</hi> or <hi>ſorrow?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Had it not then been fit, to lay aſide</l>
                  <l>Some part of what, in <hi>Vanity</hi> and <hi>Pride</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Hath been conſum'd; their <hi>ſufferings</hi> to relieve,</l>
                  <l>VVho cannot from the <hi>Publick purſe</hi> receive</l>
                  <l>VVhat is their due, until <hi>GOD</hi> ſhall reſtore</l>
                  <l>Abilities, to make that <hi>Pittance</hi> more?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Conſider, (ſince among you there are ſome,</l>
                  <l>VVho, do believe, <hi>a Kingdome is to come,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhereof <hi>CHRIST</hi> muſt be <hi>King</hi>) whether or no</l>
                  <l>Your <hi>Government,</hi> ſhould not be modell'd ſo;</l>
                  <l>That, when the <hi>People,</hi> ſhall Elect by <hi>Voyce</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Double Truſtees; GOD</hi> ſhould by <hi>lot</hi> make choyce</l>
                  <l>Of which him pleaſeth? VVhen that we have had</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Option,</hi> wherefore ſhould not His be made?</l>
                  <l>So 'twas, when <hi>Iſr'el,</hi> firſt a <hi>King</hi> enjoy'd,</l>
                  <l>And, when the firſt <hi>Apoſtleſhip</hi> was voyd.</l>
                  <l>Who would not be content to <hi>ſtand</hi> or <hi>fall</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVith what, would ſo indifferent be to all?</l>
                  <l>Or, not ſubmit to him, who will become,</l>
                  <l>Do what we can, the Giver of our <hi>Doom?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or, who will this oppoſe, but they who doubt</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>GOD,</hi> will in his <hi>Elections,</hi> leave them out?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>More might be ſaid: But, you know how to draw</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Body</hi> of a <hi>Lyon,</hi> by the <hi>Paw.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If, theſe things, you conſider; and ſhall do,</l>
                  <l>Your beſt endeavour to conform thereto,</l>
                  <l>This, I am ſure of, (though I cannot tell</l>
                  <l>VVhat will be done) that, all they, ſhall do well</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe Conſciences, unfeignedly atteſt</l>
                  <l>That, they, to do all well, have done their beſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>How pleaſing, this will prove, well know I not;</l>
                  <l>But, how I might have pleaſed, well I wot.</l>
                  <l>If, I, had flattered thoſe men in their waies,</l>
                  <l>VVho, whatſoev'r they merit, look for praiſe.</l>
                  <l>If, Pillows to their Elbowes I had ſow'd,</l>
                  <l>Sooth'd up the <hi>Covetous,</hi> fawn'd on the <hi>Proud,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And been like many other, ſo ripe-witted,</l>
                  <l>My <hi>Poems</hi> with their humours to have fitted:</l>
                  <l>Had I, another been, not he I am,</l>
                  <l>None knowing what I was, or, whence I came;</l>
                  <l>Then, had (as I did) <hi>thirty years ago,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Foretold what ſhould be, and, what ſee they do</l>
                  <l>Accordingly fufill'd; and then, had got</l>
                  <l>By that <hi>ſucceſs,</hi> (which often faileth not)</l>
                  <l>Amongſt the <hi>People,</hi> ſuch a <hi>reputation,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As they, who ſeem to ſpeak by <hi>Revelation;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It may be I had been a Saint eſteem'd</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Madmen</hi> are in <hi>Turky;</hi> or, now ſeem'd</l>
                  <l>Leſs deſpicable; or, elſe, my <hi>predictions</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Had been as well regarded as thoſe Fictions</l>
                  <l>Or fooliſh lying <hi>Propheſies,</hi> by which</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Impoſtors,</hi> this deluded age bewitch.</l>
                  <l>If, I, on that advantage, had made known</l>
                  <l>Some <hi>Crotchets</hi> or <hi>Chimera's</hi> of mine own,</l>
                  <l>For <hi>ſelfiſh ends;</hi> or, had I then pretended</l>
                  <l>To ſome <hi>new-light;</hi> ſuch <hi>Novelties</hi> commended</l>
                  <l>To his <hi>age,</hi> as are pleaſing, at this day.</l>
                  <l>Or had I, (which, I could, as well as they</l>
                  <l>VVho practiſe it) put on the tempting <hi>Dreſs</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of <hi>ſeeming zeal,</hi> and <hi>formal-holineſs;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Forborn to <hi>speak,</hi> what few men love to <hi>hear;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Not bid them leave, what no man can forbear;</l>
                  <l>And, in thoſe things complide which moſt affect;</l>
                  <l>I might have been the Father of ſome Sect:</l>
                  <l>Yea, ſo, ſhould have been favoured perchance,</l>
                  <l>As to have got ſome <hi>temporal advance:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For, few men, (could my heart therewith com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply)</l>
                  <l>Had better means, for ſuch a <hi>cheat,</hi> then <hi>I.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But, theſe were not my <hi>Aims,</hi> &amp; I have gain'd</l>
                  <l>As much, as I had hope to have attain'd.</l>
                  <l>And, having fully prov'd what is in men,</l>
                  <l>VVill henceforth lay by, my <hi>displeaſing Pen:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Not doubting, but this <hi>Letter,</hi> will effect</l>
                  <l>As much as whilſt I live, I muſt expect.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:116002:15"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>I, now have writ enough, to that intent</l>
                  <l>VVhich firſt I had; yea, much more then I ment</l>
                  <l>VVhen I began, this; and thereby make known</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Cauſe,</hi> more worthy heeding, then mine own;</l>
                  <l>Wherein, if <hi>I</hi> prevail hereby, no more</l>
                  <l>Then, by what <hi>I</hi> have written heretofore,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I,</hi> ſhall believe th' effect would be much leſs</l>
                  <l>Hereafter, ſhould I, any more expreſs.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The <hi>Preface</hi> laſt year to my <hi>SALT</hi> on <hi>SALT,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Fore-warned (and <hi>I</hi> think it not my fault</l>
                  <l>If none regard it) that, to us, <hi>this year</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Effects <hi>of dreadful Thunders,</hi> would appear;</l>
                  <l>And, ſo it comes to paſs: yet, little heeded,</l>
                  <l>Save as things, which have <hi>caſually</hi> ſucceeded:</l>
                  <l>I'll therefore, henceforth let them credit give</l>
                  <l>To what they <hi>dream, and I do not believe.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Enough is here writ, to make moſt of thoſe</l>
                  <l>That ſhall be <hi>Knaves,</hi> or <hi>Fools,</hi> to be my Foes.</l>
                  <l>And, where can I live, (unleſs <hi>God</hi> ſhall pleaſe)</l>
                  <l>Where, <hi>I</hi> can long be ſafe from ſome of theſe?</l>
                  <l>But, in their preſence, he my <hi>Table spreads;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>My <hi>Soul,</hi> nor their <hi>Power,</hi> nor their <hi>Malice</hi> dreads;</l>
                  <l>He, heretofore, hath me defended from</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Purpoſes,</hi> and will, for, <hi>time to come,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In that which moſt concerns me; though men may</l>
                  <l>Take <hi>Life, Eſtate,</hi> and outward things, away.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> have already <hi>ſaid,</hi> and <hi>Writ</hi> enough,</l>
                  <l>For <hi>men prophane,</hi> and <hi>Hypocrites</hi> to ſcoff:</l>
                  <l>Therefore, henceforth, let each man do the thing</l>
                  <l>That likes him, as when <hi>Iſr'el</hi> had no king.</l>
                  <l>Let him, that will be <hi>wilful,</hi> have his <hi>will:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Let him that's <hi>filthy,</hi> ſo continue ſtill,</l>
                  <l>Until another, to ſupply my <hi>room,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shall with a more prevailing <hi>Spirit</hi> come.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Look to thy ſelf, Oh <hi>BRITAIN!</hi> I will here</l>
                  <l>No more be thy deſpis'd <hi>REMEMBRANCER:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For, as thoſe, who (when they neglects did meet,</l>
                  <l>Were bid, <hi>to ſhake the duſt from off their feet</hi>)</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I,</hi> am excus'd; and, 'tis not my belief,</l>
                  <l>That, <hi>I</hi> am bound to preach unto the <hi>Deaf,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And caſt away my <hi>Pearls,</hi> as I have done,</l>
                  <l>Where they and I, ſhall ſtill be trampled on.</l>
                  <l>My <hi>Soul,</hi> is clear from any <hi>blood of thine;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>GOD grant, thou mayſt as guiltleſs be of <hi>mine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thine <hi>own,</hi> and <hi>other mens;</hi> and at thy need,</l>
                  <l>Speed better, in thy <hi>ſuits,</hi> then yet I ſpeed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I will no more, affright thee with <hi>Alarms</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By my <hi>Predictions,</hi> of approaching harms,</l>
                  <l>As in times paſt; nor add to thy <hi>offence,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By minding thee, of thine <hi>impenitence;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nor ſeem to play the <hi>Fool,</hi> to make thoſe <hi>wiſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who, will not ſee, wherein their <hi>ſafety lies:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But, ceaſe to meddle in thoſe <hi>Publick-matters,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which, thy <hi>Falſe Prophets,</hi> and <hi>Prognoſticaters,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Have puzzell'd: But, to <hi>him,</hi> a ſuitor be,</l>
                  <l>VVho, from what's threatned, can deliver thee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To <hi>works of this kind,</hi> here, I fix a <hi>bound,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>This, is the laſt time, wherein I will ſound</l>
                  <l>My <hi>Trumpet</hi> to theſe <hi>Nations;</hi> or make known</l>
                  <l>Ought which concerns <hi>thy matters,</hi> or <hi>mine own</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In <hi>publick wiſe,</hi> or, in a <hi>private way,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Save, as my <hi>Neighbours,</hi> either do, or may;</l>
                  <l>Unleſs, I, from <hi>within,</hi> have ſuch a <hi>Call</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As cannot ſafely be diſpens'd withal:</l>
                  <l>Or, elſe, an <hi>outward Call</hi> from thoſe who may</l>
                  <l>Command me, if they think, that I can ſay</l>
                  <l>VVhat to the <hi>Publick welfare</hi> will relate:</l>
                  <l>But, there is little likelyhood of that;</l>
                  <l>And, therefore, I intend to ſpare my breath,</l>
                  <l>To vent my <hi>Thoughts</hi> in private till my death.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oh! that I fail not, of my</hi> expectations,</l>
                  <l>(<hi>In this</hi> dark Den, <hi>of</hi> cruel habitations,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>By outward or by inward perturbations</hi>)</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To take thy Kingdom, (Wherein, at this day,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thine enemies and mine, the</hi> Tyrants <hi>play</hi>)</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>COME, come, LORD JESU, quickly come away.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="prose">
               <p>I begin this <hi>Wandring-Epiſtle,</hi> with reſpect to my preſent <hi>temporal condition</hi> onely; without ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the leaſt thought of the preceding <hi>Cataſtrophe.</hi> But, as it heretofore befel <hi>Sampſon,</hi> (and hath oft befallen many of <hi>Gods</hi> ſervants in their <hi>Frailties</hi>) with the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> he muſt firſt have occaſion given, by an outward injury, before he could be rowzed up to execute <hi>GOD</hi>'s Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance upon the Enemies of his <hi>Country;</hi> ſo, before my <hi>Dull Fleſh</hi> could be capable of admitting that <hi>publick-ſpirit</hi> to come upon me, which might ſufficiently emholden me to declare what is at this time neceſſary to be offered to my Country-mens Conſideration, ſhe muſt be firſt reduced to a great ſtraight, by the hazard of her too much beloved temporal Concernments: And, as <hi>Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> upon the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> affirm of the <hi>Prophet DAVID,</hi> it hath now happened unto me. VVhilſt he (as they conceive) was contemplating and complaining of thoſe his <hi>perſonal Perſecutions</hi> and <hi>Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions</hi> wherein he was a Type of the <hi>MESSIAS,</hi> he was ſuddenly tranſported above the ſenſe of his own <hi>Sufferings,</hi> into <hi>Raptures</hi> prophetically expreſſing the <hi>perſecutions</hi> and <hi>paſſions</hi> of his and our <hi>REDEEMER: In</hi> like manner, <hi>I,</hi> whoſe preſent <hi>outward Eſtate,</hi> much reſembles this <hi>Commonwealths</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:116002:16"/>confuſed, needy, and hazardous Condition, (as <hi>I</hi> have heretofore particularly demonſtrated) ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a purpoſe, as aforeſaid to expreſs my <hi>perſonal Grievances</hi> onely, in order to a timely <hi>Redreſs,</hi> was carried by a <hi>Poetical Rapture,</hi> into an <hi>unpremeditated Apprehenſion,</hi> of what may poſſibly come to paſs, and neerly relates to this <hi>Republicks</hi> well or ill being, as the <hi>pre-conditioned means</hi> of her wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare ſhall be neglected or performed; and to touch alſo upon ſome <hi>Particulars,</hi> of a higher con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment; even upon ſuch as relate to the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of <hi>CHRIST</hi> and his <hi>Saints,</hi> with a Hint upon ſomewhat thereto pertinent; which being miſapprehended by many who wait for that <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> may occaſion trouble to themſelves and others, not without infringement of the <hi>Civil-peace,</hi> and diſhonour to that <hi>spiritual Kingdome</hi> which we pray for, if they be not wary of thoſe <hi>carnal deluſions</hi> which the <hi>Enemy</hi> thereof ſeeks to mingle with their <hi>dim Notions</hi> of that <hi>myſterious Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy,</hi> to make them thereby ſomewhat inſtrumental to prolong his Empire in the myſtical <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The latter part of this <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> was on a ſuddain dictated to me in the Language of the <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes:</hi> therefore, though <hi>Verſe</hi> be ſo much grown out of eſteem and faſhon, more then it was when <hi>I</hi> firſt began to <hi>verſifie,</hi> that amongſt moſt men it is in as little eſteem as <hi>I my ſelf</hi> am; and ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuneably accented by moſt <hi>Readers,</hi> that in reading them, they mar the ſenſe, and make worſe Muſick then a Smiths File, or <hi>ſcraping of Trenchers:</hi> Nevertheleſs, <hi>I</hi> have inſerted them as they were received from my <hi>Inspirer,</hi> as pertinent both to my <hi>Cauſe,</hi> and to them who ſhould aſſume it into Conſideration. <hi>Farewell:</hi> who thou art, into whoſe hands this will come, <hi>I</hi> know not: But, if thou ſhalt accept it, and make uſe thereof according to my reaſonable <hi>Requeſts,</hi> thou art <hi>one of thoſe,</hi> to whom it was originally intended, by thy <hi>Servant</hi> in all reaſonable ſervices,</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>Geo. Wither.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Auguſt</hi> 10. 1659.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="epiphonema">
            <head>EPIPHONEMA.</head>
            <l>THe more, I <hi>muſe,</hi> the more I may,</l>
            <l>Till <hi>night,</hi> ends in <hi>eternal day:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>For, ev'ry hour, brings forth new things,</l>
            <l>From whence, <hi>new matter</hi> dayly ſprings,</l>
            <l>Whereof, I ſhall but ſpeak in vain,</l>
            <l>Whilſt my <hi>Corruptions</hi> do remain:</l>
            <l>But, when I must depart to <hi>Him,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Who nor <hi>begun,</hi> nor ends in <hi>Time,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And, hence, quite out of ſight, am gone,</l>
            <l>My <hi>words</hi> will more be thought upon.</l>
            <l>Or they (when recknings are ſet right)</l>
            <l>Will help make <hi>meaſure</hi> and <hi>full weight.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Enſuing times,</hi> will uſeful make them,</l>
            <l>Tho I, (in ſcoff, call'd <hi>Prophet</hi>) ſpake them:</l>
            <l>And, when of <hi>nothing,</hi> I have need,</l>
            <l>They, paradventure, or their <hi>ſeed,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Who in my life-time, have undone me,</l>
            <l>Will (dead) beſtow a Grave upon me;</l>
            <l>As they that (iſſuing from their wombs</l>
            <l>Who ſlew them) built the <hi>Prophets</hi> tombs.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:116002:16"/>
            <head>A POST-SCRIPT.</head>
            <p>DUring the Interval betwixt the laſt <hi>Aſſembly</hi> called a <hi>Parliament,</hi> and the reſtoring of this, I became ſo ſenſible of that ſad condition, whereinto we were generally brought, that, I was ſtupified as to all endeavourings concerning my own <hi>Estate;</hi> and thought they would be as little effectual, as to go about to repair a <hi>Lodging</hi> in a <hi>Houſe</hi> every part whereof was in a <hi>flame;</hi> the <hi>foundations</hi> ruined, and the Superſtructures ready to fall. Therefore, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to be every mans duty to do what he could to preſerve the <hi>Common-intereſt,</hi> I expelled <hi>ſelfneſs,</hi> as much as poſſibly out of my thought, for a few days; and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amining mine own heart, what <hi>expedients</hi> it could offer thereunto; I apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that the firſt <hi>step</hi> toward preventing what I feared, would be a <hi>right under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing,</hi> of that much <hi>miſtaken Cauſe,</hi> which hath been lately carried on through many <hi>Labyrinths, Turnings</hi> and <hi>Returnings,</hi> until moſt men had quite loſt the true <hi>Notion,</hi> of that, for which, they firſt contended; inſomuch, that ſome <hi>Obliquely,</hi> and ſome other <hi>Diametrically</hi> oppoſed it, to the engaging of many thouſands into <hi>Factions</hi> deſtructive both to the <hi>Publick,</hi> and to their own <hi>private ſafety and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare.</hi> I perceived likewiſe, that ſome had honeſtly, but imperfectly; and ſome ſo maliciouſly ſtated our <hi>Good old Cauſe,</hi> (as they termed it in ſcoff) that it made men abhor it, who had formerly, thereto adhered; and to occaſion thoſe mutinous and ſeditious <hi>Conſpiracies,</hi> which are newly broken forth into <hi>Rebellion,</hi> likely to joyn a <hi>Foraign Invaſion</hi> to <hi>Domeſtick Inſurrections;</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> in hope to prevent, I ſtated the ſaid <hi>Cauſe</hi> according to my underſtanding, before the Reſtauration of this <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> with an addition of ſome <hi>Preparatory conceptions,</hi> which I thought uſeful toward ſuch a <hi>ſettlement,</hi> as that, whereof our late <hi>Innovations</hi> and <hi>Changes,</hi> had for the preſent, made us moſt capable: And, I ſo fitted (as I conceived) my illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our juſt <hi>Cauſe,</hi> with <hi>ſimple expreſſions,</hi> ſuitable to their capacities, whoſe right underſtanding thereof, is moſt needful, that, I thought it might have much conduced to the quieting their <hi>ſpirits,</hi> whoſe <hi>miſapprehenſions</hi> only (and not a malevolent wilfulneſs) had made them to be verbally, or <hi>actively,</hi> oppoſers of their own <hi>Intereſt:</hi> For, without impoſing upon them, any <hi>Magiſterial Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities,</hi> of whoſe validity they can have no certain knowledge (as they uſually do, who ſeek to inſlave mens <hi>Conſciences,</hi> no leſs then their <hi>Bodies,</hi> and <hi>Eſtates,</hi> by frighting them, with <hi>Laws</hi> made either without their aſſent, or with a conſtrained aſſent, by thoſe <hi>Tyrants</hi> who had uſurped upon their juſt <hi>Rights</hi>) I deduced their <hi>claim,</hi> from the <hi>Original</hi> thereof; evidencing it, by ſuch <hi>Principles,</hi> and <hi>Reaſons</hi> only, as the <hi>Common people,</hi> may be <hi>Judges</hi> of; and by bringing to their remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, ſuch <hi>Truths</hi> and <hi>tranſactions,</hi> to evince the juſtneſs of their <hi>Cauſe,</hi> as are
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:116002:17"/>for the moſt part known unto themſelves; eſpecially as they have relation to the late <hi>King,</hi> and thoſe, who ſucceeded him, in his <hi>Tyranny.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This, I reſolved to publiſh, till the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> of this <hi>Parliament;</hi> at which time I thought it would neither be ſo needfully nor ſo warrantably done, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard there then appeared a lawful <hi>viſible power,</hi> able enough to proſecute that work, without my <hi>Notions,</hi> though perhaps, their <hi>humility</hi> would, and their <hi>Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> might have made ſome of them ſerviceable: and upon that ſuppoſition, I was once again, minded to communicate my <hi>Conceptions</hi> aforementioned in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, ſince their <hi>Reſtauration,</hi> together with my PROTECTORIA, (which is a <hi>Collection</hi> of ſuch <hi>Addreſſes</hi> and other <hi>Writings,</hi> as I had compoſed in relation to the <hi>Protectors,</hi> whilſt they were in <hi>being,</hi>) as not impertinent to the facilitating of their <hi>work</hi> without the doors of their <hi>Houſe:</hi> But, I have already, contributed ſo much of my Eſtate, toward <hi>publick ſervices,</hi> and, ſo much is detained from me, that I was not able to print it, at my own coſt; and (I, not then purpoſing, to be known <hi>Author</hi> thereof, leſt it might have the leſs eſteem) no other man, to my knowledge, would put himſelf to that charge: Moreover, here hath been e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſince, ſuch a multitude of <hi>ſingle ſheets</hi> and <hi>Pamphlets,</hi> daily fluttering about e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very mans <hi>ears,</hi> buſying their <hi>eyes,</hi> and filling their Pockets, that my <hi>Papers</hi> would probably have been obſcured among them; And, I have alſo, in this <hi>Epiſtle</hi> bound my ſelf from publiſhing any more hereafter of this nature, except, upon a <hi>Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious accompt,</hi> or by the command of my <hi>Superiours.</hi> Therefore if any of my <hi>Writings</hi> laſt mentioned, or any other, but ſuch as have been formerly printed, (or by command, and as aforeſaid) do come forth by their procurement who have, or ſhall have <hi>Copies</hi> of them; Let not the Trouble, or diſcontent, which thereby may be occaſioned, be imputed unto me. <hi>I will add but this Corollary. My ſins have juſtly deſerved that God ſhould permit me to be oppreſſed; Therefore, though with penitence, I have made uſe of this Epiſtle, among other means for deliverance; I truſt not thereupon; nor upon any thing which I can ſay or do, or which any other man can ſay or do for me; but in Gods free mercies only; and if he will not deliver me, I will not be delivered.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Geo. Wither.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Faults Eſcaped.</head>
            <p>In the laſt line of the Title-page, for <hi>turn,</hi> read <hi>cure:</hi> page 14. line 28. for <hi>the ſame,</hi> read <hi>ſome.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
